<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-09T18:32:29+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/rss.xml</id><title type="html">Yegor Bugayenko</title><subtitle>Yegor Bugayenko</subtitle><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Patents and Their Claims</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/06/09/patent-claim.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patents and Their Claims" /><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/06/09/patent-claim</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/06/09/patent-claim.html"><![CDATA[<p>If you, like me, are not a patent attorney and don’t understand patent law,
but your boss asks you to turn your recently written piece of code into
a patent, read on. The boss most probably won’t ask you to write the entire
patent. Instead, he will ask you to prepare a quick summary of the invention
(usually, a few slides) and then a hired lawyer will turn it into
a full-scale patent application. If you understand the purpose of patents,
the mechanics of patent offices, and the format of a patent claim, you will
do just fine.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="And Justice for All (1979) by Norman Jewison" src="/images/2024/06/and-justice-for-all.jpg" longdesc="#03ca432c" /><figcaption id="03ca432c">And Justice for All (1979) by Norman Jewison</figcaption></figure>

<p><strong>What are patents for?</strong>
Initially invented as a tool to encourage innocent inventors,
they are currently used mostly as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent_war">weapon</a>
either to bully larger organizations or
to defend them against bullying. It all started in Italy in 1474,
when a three-year “grant” <a href="https://guides.slv.vic.gov.au/patents/history">was given</a>
to Filippo Brunelleschi for “some machine or kind of ship,”
for a period of three years. Since then, <a href="https://www.wipo.int/en/ipfactsandfigures/patents">over 3.5 million patents</a>
have been issued by different <em>patent offices</em> around the globe to respected
inventors.</p>

<p><strong>What is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent_office">patent office</a>?</strong>
It’s a security organization funded by a government:
<a href="https://www.uspto.gov/">USPTO</a> in the United States,
<a href="https://www.epo.org/en">EPO</a> in the European Union,
<a href="https://english.cnipa.gov.cn/">CNIPA</a> in China,
<a href="https://rospatent.gov.ru/en">Rospatent</a> in Russia,
<a href="https://www.ipos.gov.sg/">IPOS</a> in Singapore,
and a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent_office">few dozen</a> in other countries.
Also, there is
<a href="https://www.wipo.int/portal/en/index.html">WIPO</a> in Geneva (Switzerland) that
coordinates the work of all other POs, so far.
They protect you if you pay them (no surprise it all started in Italy!)</p>

<p>Let’s say you invent a new file compression algorithm and
you don’t want anyone to use it without your permission. First, you pay
<a href="https://www.uspto.gov/learning-and-resources/fees-and-payment/uspto-fee-schedule">$320</a>
to USPTO and submit an application. Then, in a few months, they assign your application
a number and call it “pending.” Then, you wait for about <a href="https://www.uspto.gov/dashboard/patents/pendency.html">3.5 years</a>
until they reply back with a decision: either you get a patent, you get nothing,
or they ask you to refine the application (most common case).
You make the changes, resubmit, they criticize, you resubmit, … and eventually
they issue a patent.</p>

<p><strong>Now what?</strong>
Your company publishes a press release, informs all investors, you
make a Facebook post so that your mom can be proud of you,
and in a few days everybody forgets about it. Because nobody cares. Until
the <em>litigation</em> day comes: your company finds out that another company is
also compressing files using the same algorithm. Or, the other way around:
they find out that the algorithm you invented is actually the algorithm they
have been quietly using for years. You both meet in a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent_court">patent court</a>.
The USPTO will be there too, since you paid them earlier.</p>

<p>If your opponent <em>does not</em> have a patent, the judge will ask them to prove
that their compression algorithm was publicly available prior to your
application. If they provide such proof, your patent will be
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent_infringement"><em>infringed</em></a>—you will lose
it, your $320 won’t be refunded, and you will pay everything you made over the last
few years to the opponent.</p>

<p>If your opponent <em>does</em> have a patent, you will have to prove that your
patent is older and <em>broader</em>. USPTO attorneys most probably won’t try to help you,
since they won’t be on your side, but simply a mediator between both of you
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_Inc._v._Samsung_Electronics_Co.">Apple vs. Samsung</a>
litigation is a good example of such a patent war). If you win,
their patent will be infringed and you will get all the profit they managed
to collect over the last years. Big win!</p>

<p><strong>What is patent breadth?</strong>
First, let’s discuss what is its <em>length</em>. You may be surprised,
but patents have pretty short lifetimes.
If you don’t extend a patent, it will expire in just <em>three years</em>. If you do want to
extend it, you must pay USPTO <a href="https://www.uspto.gov/patents/basics/manage">again</a>
and much more than you paid the first time:
<a href="https://www.uspto.gov/patents/basics/manage">$2,000</a> in 3 years,
$3,760 in 7 years,
$7,700 in 11 years.
Not cheap, huh?</p>

<p>Now, the breadth. Consider three <em>patent claims</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“An apparatus consisting of a file reader; a file writer; and a compressor.”</li>
  <li>“A file compressing method comprising
a reader of JPEG files;
a probability distribution calculator;
a discrete transformer;
a bla-bla-bla optimizer;
an intermediate storage;
a writer of JPEG files.”</li>
  <li>“A Lempel–Ziv based data compression method comprising:
converting input stream into ψ-tokens;
reducing redundancy via Prishvin Ω(x) factorials;
serializing through Turgenev 𝛾-extremums.”</li>
</ul>

<p>The first claim is much broader: it probably covers all possible file compressing
software tools ever created. Such a broad patent claim won’t even be
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patentability">accepted</a>
by USPTO if you file it. They will do a quick search of <em>prior art</em> (other
patents previously issued) and reject you on the basis of a lack of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novelty_%28patent%29"><em>novelty</em></a>.
The second claim is narrower, but still pretty broad, since the architecture
of other existing compressors may be very similar to the described one.
The third claim is the most narrow and the most specific (although, have
absolutely no sense, it is made up).</p>

<p><strong>How to write a good patent claim?</strong>
There is no such thing as an objectively <a href="https://support.lens.org/knowledge-base/what-are-claims/">good claim</a>,
since it depends on the
situation in the market. If the territory of innovation is not yet developed
and you are a pioneer, a broader and shorter (by the length in years, not the
number of words) patent is better. If you are making a small improvement
to a well-developed prior art, better make the patent narrower and longer.</p>

<p>A <em>patent claim</em> is the key element of a patent application. While the rest
of the document may be written by a patent attorney, I strongly suggest
you write the claim. At least its first version.
There is a more or less strict structure of a claim:
preamble, transitional phrase, and body:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Preamble</th>
      <th>Transitional Phrase</th>
      <th>Body</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>An apparatus</td>
      <td>consisting of</td>
      <td>a file reader; a file writer; and a compressor.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>A file compressing method</td>
      <td>comprising</td>
      <td>a reader of JPEG files; a probability distribution calculator; a discrete transformer; a bla-bla-bla optimizer; an intermediate storage; a writer of JPEG files.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>A Lempel–Ziv based data compression method</td>
      <td>comprising</td>
      <td>converting input stream into ψ-tokens, reducing redundancy via Prishvin Ω(x) factorials, serializing through Turgenev 𝛾-extremums.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The <a href="https://www.wilmerhale.com/insights/publications/patent-claim-preambles-july-16-2003">preamble</a>
must position your invention among all other devices
and methods in the prior art. The “an apparatus” preamble is very broad:
it could mean any device in the world, even not only
from the computing domain. The “a file compressing method” preamble
is much narrower, while “a Lempel–Ziv based data compression method” is the
most narrow one, with almost no ambiguity for the interpretation.</p>

<p>The body of a <a href="https://ocpatentlawyer.com/basics-writing-claim-patent-application/">patent claim</a>
must iterate the elements that constitute
the invention. The fewer elements you include in this list, the broader
the patent will be. The broader the patent, the easier to infringe. Well, unless
you invent something revolutionary new. On the other hand, the more elements,
the narrower the patent, the weaker it is as a weapon. It will be very hard
to use a narrow patent in a patent litigation.</p>

<p>The claim must also be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inventive_step_and_non-obviousness"><em>non-obvious</em></a>,
meaning that your invention has to be
an adequate distance beyond or above the state of the art. Say, a new file
format is invented for graphic images and you submit a patent application
for a ZIP compressor that can also compress files in this new format.
If there is no novelty in the compression algorithm itself, such a patent
would be considered obvious since it’s not far away from prior art: existing
ZIP compressors can deal with this file format, even though they don’t know
about it yet.</p>

<p><strong>How do you decide?</strong>
It is your responsibility as a patent author to decide how broad
and how long your patent must be. Then, a patent attorney will help you turn your
patent claim into a patent application (charging a
<a href="https://patentattorneyworldwide.com/us/much-patent-attorney-us-charges-stage-getting-patent/">few thousand dollars</a>
along the way), and then, hopefully, the litigation day will come and you will win
a lot of money. Most probably this will never happen and the patent will
remain a nice badge on your CV and your company’s website.</p>

<p>By the way, it is important to remember that if you want to get similar protection
in another country, you will have to pay their patent office separately.
Just like you pay every time a different mafia boss for protection when
you want to work in the territories they control.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you are a programer, then even if a lawyer may help you write a patent application, your job is to prepare a proper patent claim, making its breadth right on.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/06/and-justice-for-all.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/06/and-justice-for-all.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Онлайн хулиганы</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/05/27/freedom-of-speech-vs-intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Онлайн хулиганы" /><published>2024-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/05/27/freedom-of-speech-vs-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/05/27/freedom-of-speech-vs-intelligence.html"><![CDATA[<p>А знаете, какое самое популярное по числу просмотров видео на YouTube?
Вот <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XqZsoesa55w">это</a>.
14 миллиардов просмотров за менее чем семь лет. И таких видео
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_most-liked_YouTube_videos">много</a>. Задаюсь
вопросом, о чем эта песня? Чему она учит? Какой вообще в ней смысл? С моей
точки зрения, сформированной когда-то давно сказками
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9C%D0%B8%D1%85%D0%B0%D0%BB%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2,_%D0%A1%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%B3%D0%B5%D0%B9_%D0%92%D0%BB%D0%B0%D0%B4%D0%B8%D0%BC%D0%B8%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Сергея Михалкова</a>,
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9C%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%88%D0%B0%D0%BA,_%D0%A1%D0%B0%D0%BC%D1%83%D0%B8%D0%BB_%D0%AF%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BB%D0%B5%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Самуила Маршака</a> и
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%91%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%82%D0%BE,_%D0%90%D0%B3%D0%BD%D0%B8%D1%8F_%D0%9B%D1%8C%D0%B2%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BD%D0%B0">Агнии Барто</a>, в этой песне смысла нет.
Но ведь он должен быть, раз её посмотрели и оценили по достоинству сотни
миллионов родителей и детей! Нет, не должен. Всё просто: что сейчас нравится миллионам, то и
является эталоном качества. Но ведь так было не всегда.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Babyshark by Pinkfong" src="/images/2024/05/babyshark.jpg" longdesc="#4e17762b" /><figcaption id="4e17762b">Babyshark by Pinkfong</figcaption></figure>

<p>Ещё несколько десятков лет назад, ни интернета, ни YouTube не существовало, а
все средства массовой информации имели редакторов или даже редакционные
коллективы, которые решали, что публиковать и доносить до зрителя, а что сразу
в корзину. Более того, ещё раньше существовали страны, в которых на
государственном уровне свирепствовала <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A6%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B7%D1%83%D1%80%D0%B0">цензура</a>, которая не только в
корзину отправляла негодный материал, но и автора в лагеря.</p>

<p>К счастью, скажете вы, те времена прошли. Наступило не просто время торжества
свободы слова, но и время почти абсолютной бесполезности редакторов и цензоров.
Несколько лет назад я испытал это на себе.
<a href="/2018/11/20/journalism.html">Дело было так</a>. Я написал техническую
<a href="/2018/03/06/speed-vs-quality.html">статью</a>
и отправил её в одно онлайн-издание. Мне отказали, объяснив почему. Я
отправил в другое издание, где мне тоже отказали, при этом назвав причину,
которая полностью противоречила первому отказу. Редакторы советовали исправить
статью в противоположных направлениях. В итоге я опубликовал статью у себя на
блоге, выступил с ней на <a href="https://youtu.be/55mwAbuDrV8">конференции</a>,
и получил куда больше просмотров
и лайков, чем, наверное, мог бы собрать в одном из этих уважаемых изданий.</p>

<p>Полагаю, что если бы подобные события происходили на 50 лет раньше,
я бы не смог опубликовать свои мысли, не удовлетворив строгих требований одного из редакторов. Меня бы
ограничила цензура. Более того, если бы я опубликовал свою статью
самостоятельно методом так называемого <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A1%D0%B0%D0%BC%D0%B8%D0%B7%D0%B4%D0%B0%D1%82">самиздата</a>, то до лагерей было бы рукой
подать (как минимум строгого выговора мне было бы не избежать). Казалось бы,
какие ужасные времена остались в прошлом, и как прекрасно, что теперь нет ни
цензуры, ни редколлегий, а есть интернет! Это только на первый взгляд.</p>

<p>Как я её понимаю, задачей цензуры является не столько ограничение творческих
порывов авторов, сколько защита всех остальных граждан от последствий этих
порывов. Ровно как полиция наказывает хулиганов не потому, что хочет причинить
им вред, а для того, чтобы защитить окружающих. Видео ролики, подобные тому, с
просмотра которого мы начали эту статью, и есть, по моему мнению, самое настоящее
онлайн-хулиганство.</p>

<p>Вы скажете, но ведь люди-то довольны. Они же смотрят, ставят лайки,
подписываются на YouTube-каналы. Какое же это хулиганство, если большинство в
восторге и показывает этот контент своим детям, а те, надо полагать, водят
пальцем по экрану и мычат от удовольствия? В том-то и дело, что последствия
бытового хулиганства нам очевидны и неприятны: ни разбитые окна, ни запах в
лифте, ни надписи на стенах в подъезде абсолютному большинству не по душе.
Последствия же онлайн-хулиганства куда более трагические, но при этом менее
очевидные для большинства: у населения снижается интеллект и
пропадает тяга к прекрасному. Это страшнее запаха в подъезде.</p>

<p>Но виноваты в этом не авторы этой незатейливой песенки и прочего подобного
контента, которым заполнен YouTube! Они лишь делают свою работу, стараясь
соответствовать запросам общества. Но вот если 50 лет назад интересы общества
были представлены строгим редактором журнала <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%AE%D0%BD%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D1%8C_(%D0%B6%D1%83%D1%80%D0%BD%D0%B0%D0%BB)">“Юность”</a> и художественным советом
фестиваля <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9F%D0%B5%D1%81%D0%BD%D1%8F_%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%B4%D0%B0">“Песня года”</a>, то теперь интересы общества представляет YouTube,
который выражает их через количество лайков. Что бы автор ни создал, он
вынужден подстраиваться под вкусы толпы, которая безусловно с огромным
восторгом будет воспринимать нецензурную лексику, шутки ниже пояса, да и просто
во всех смыслах порнографию.</p>

<p>Поскольку средний человек не способен отличить онлайн-хулиганов от достойных авторов,
авторы вынуждены хулиганить, чтобы заслужить лайки (а значит, заработать
гонорар). Любимая нами свобода слова, которую уважаемая нами фирма Google
(владелец YouTube) защищает, позволяя размещать у себя контент практически
любого качества и содержания, и есть главный виновник и провокатор
онлайн-хулиганства.</p>

<p>Дописываю эту статью, находясь в Китае. Пару дней назад беседовал с одним
знакомым китайцем, и он рассказал, что на их онлайн-видео платформах существует
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A6%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B7%D1%83%D1%80%D0%B0_%D0%B2_%D0%9A%D0%B8%D1%82%D0%B0%D0%B5">строгая цензура</a>. Запрещено выкладывать всё, что по мнению правительства не
соответствует моральному облику строителя <del>коммунизма</del> здорового общества. И
конечно, запрещены любые видео ролики политического характера. Может быть,
такие ограничения имеют смысл, учитывая всё сказанное выше?</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="свобода" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Свобода слова помогает авторам быть услышанным, но при этом провоцирует и делает невозможным наказания онлайн хулиганов, в которых неизбежно превращаются авторы, стараясь заработать лайки.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/05/babyshark.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/05/babyshark.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Куликовы поля</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/04/02/kulikovo-pole.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Куликовы поля" /><published>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/04/02/kulikovo-pole</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/04/02/kulikovo-pole.html"><![CDATA[<p>Я не историк и даже в школе историю не любил. Не любил, но верил,
что так все и было: и <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%92%D0%B5%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D1%84%D1%80%D0%B0%D0%BD%D1%86%D1%83%D0%B7%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D1%80%D0%B5%D0%B2%D0%BE%D0%BB%D1%8E%D1%86%D0%B8%D1%8F">Французская революция</a>, и <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%92%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B5_%D0%A1%D0%BF%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%82%D0%B0%D0%BA%D0%B0">восстание Спартака</a>,
и война <a href="атилла">Аттилы</a> с Римом, и охоты на мамонтов с последующими иллюстрациями
на стенах древних пещер. Все это было именно так, как рассказывали
нам учителя истории (они в моем детстве почему-то часто менялись).
Позже, когда появился Internet, я узнал о <a href="https://chronologia.org/">Новой Хронологии</a> и стал
скептиком — перестал верить на слово тому, что говорят историки. Стал в любом
описании событий прошлого искать альтернативные версии. Еще позже
я узнал, что это называется <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A2%D0%B5%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%8F_%D0%B7%D0%B0%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B0">конспирологией</a> и в порядочном обществе
осуждается, <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transhumanism_Inc.">Пелевин</a> не даст соврать.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Поединок Пересвета с Челубеем, Михаил Авилов" src="/images/2024/04/peresvet-i-chelubej.jpg" longdesc="#516b4ef8" /><figcaption id="516b4ef8">Поединок Пересвета с Челубеем, Михаил Авилов</figcaption></figure>

<p>Спрашивается, можем ли мы достоверно утверждать, что именно происходило, скажем,
шесть веков назад, когда ни Instagram ни даже <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%BF%D0%B5%D1%87%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B5">книгопечатания</a> еще не существовало?
Достоверно не можем. Можем лишь предполагать, какие события могли произойти,
опираясь на имеющиеся в нашем распоряжении артефакты
и учитывая возможность их фальсификации. Чем артефактов меньше и чем они старше, тем
больше возможностей совершить ошибку. А ошибки совершаются, и часто.</p>

<p>Например, до недавнего времени считалось, что
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%98%D0%B2%D0%B0%D0%BD_%D0%93%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%B7%D0%BD%D1%8B%D0%B9">Иван Грозный</a> убил своего сына, ударив тяжелым царским посохом по голове.
Откуда нам это было <a href="https://histrf.ru/read/articles/gibiel-nasliednika-mogh-li-ivan-groznyi-ubit-starshiegho-syna">известно</a>?
Через пять лет после якобы убийства,
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9F%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%81%D0%B5%D0%B2%D0%B8%D0%BD%D0%BE,_%D0%90%D0%BD%D1%82%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%BE">Антонио Поссевино</a>, папский легат и секретарь ордена <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%98%D0%B5%D0%B7%D1%83%D0%B8%D1%82">иезуитов</a>,
опубликовал трактат <a href="http://moscowstate.ru/possevino-a-istoricheskie-sochineniya-o-rossii-xvi-v-moskoviya-livoniya-i-dr/">“Московия”</a>,
в котором и описал события, о которых якобы имел точные сведения.
Затем, через тридцать лет, когда у власти уже была <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A0%D0%BE%D0%BC%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B2%D1%8B">династия Романовых</a>, эту версию
повторили, например, в <a href="http://lib.pushkinskijdom.ru/Default.aspx?tabid=10940">“Хронографе”</a> 1617 года.
Еще через двести лет, <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D0%B0%D1%80%D0%B0%D0%BC%D0%B7%D0%B8%D0%BD,_%D0%9D%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B0%D0%B9_%D0%9C%D0%B8%D1%85%D0%B0%D0%B9%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Карамзин Николай Михайлович</a> в своей
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%98%D1%81%D1%82%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%8F_%D0%B3%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%83%D0%B4%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%B0_%D0%A0%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%81%D0%B8%D0%B9%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B3%D0%BE">“Истории Государства Российского”</a>
пересказал версию легата, а еще через полвека
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A0%D0%B5%D0%BF%D0%B8%D0%BD,_%D0%98%D0%BB%D1%8C%D1%8F_%D0%95%D1%84%D0%B8%D0%BC%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Иван Репин</a> написал свою <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%98%D0%B2%D0%B0%D0%BD_%D0%93%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%B7%D0%BD%D1%8B%D0%B9_%D0%B8_%D1%81%D1%8B%D0%BD_%D0%B5%D0%B3%D0%BE_%D0%98%D0%B2%D0%B0%D0%BD_16_%D0%BD%D0%BE%D1%8F%D0%B1%D1%80%D1%8F_1581_%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%B4%D0%B0">известную картину</a>.
Однако, в 1963 году, гробница царя и его семьи
<a href="https://cyberleninka.ru/article/n/a-byl-li-ubit-syn-tsarya-ivana-iv-groznogo/viewer">была вскрыта</a>
и очевидных признаков убийства обнаружено не было: в волосах царевича не было крови.
Более того, были обнаружены признаки отравления, но не сына, а всей семьи.
Таким образом, версия об убийстве, в которую верил весь мир более четырех веков,
оказалсь лишь выдумкой итальянца закрепленной Карамзиным.</p>

<aside class="quote">
Если из истории убрать всю ложь, то совершенно не факт, что там останется одна только правда, может совсем ничего не остаться.
<span><a href="https://ru.wikiquote.org/wiki/%D0%A1%D1%82%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%B8%D1%81%D0%BB%D0%B0%D0%B2_%D0%95%D0%B6%D0%B8_%D0%9B%D0%B5%D1%86">Станислав Ежи Лец</a></span>
</aside>

<p>Однако, не стоит поспешно обвинять Карамзина. Попытайтесь поставить себя на его место.
Ведь если взглянуть на ситуацию с его точки зрения: какой-то Иван Грозный, два
с половиной века назад, убил кого-то, или нет — разве это имеет принципиальное
значение? Задача была поставлена, заказчик ждал выполнения, а зарплата
была <a href="https://www.bbc.com/russian/features-38030502">внушительной</a>.
Так почему бы не написать, что убийство имело место, особенно если
есть “первоисточник”, на который можно опереться? Пусть потомки рассудят,
если им это будет важно: они могут провести эксгумацию, сопоставить
факты, написать диссертации. “По крайней мере, я никого не убивал”, — так,
вероятно, размышлял Николай Михайлович, задумываясь о том, соответствует ли
истине рассказ того итальянца, о правдивости которого он не имел
представления.</p>

<p>А если бы Карамзин пожелал докопаться до истины, не обращая внимания на возможную
потерю гонорара, какие бы методы и инструменты он мог использовать? Каковы
доступные историкам средства для выявления правды? Ещё более важный вопрос
касается точности каждого из этих инструментов: какова их погрешность? Можно
предположить, что арсенал методов у историков похож на тот, что используют
криминалисты: на основе косвенных и прямых доказательств необходимо воссоздать
образ событий, стараясь обеспечить согласованность улик. Также стоит принимать
в расчёт показания свидетелей, при этом учитывая степень их заинтересованности
в определённой интерпретации событий.</p>

<p>После завершения работы криминалистов следователь объединяет все собранные
улики, реконструирует картину произошедшего и направляет материалы в суд, где
обе стороны получают возможность высказаться. С одной стороны, адвокаты ищут
неточности в собранных данных, стараясь убедить суд в том, что предложенная
реконструкция событий неверна — например, что Иван Грозный не убивал своего
сына. С другой стороны, прокурор усиливает доводы в пользу правдоподобности
своей версии событий. В итоге суд формирует своё, субъективное мнение о
случившемся и выносит вердикт. Этот процесс является частью судебного права,
представляющего собой механизм установления истины в правовом государстве.
Наличие доступной всем гражданам судебной системы — несомненный признак
развитого общества. К этой мысли мы ещё вернёмся через минуту.</p>

<p>Пока же, от времен Ивана IV перейдем к ещё более древним эпохам и к событию,
предположительно, случившемуся двумя столетиями ранее:
грандиозному сражению 8-го сентября 1380-го года между народным ополчением
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%94%D0%BC%D0%B8%D1%82%D1%80%D0%B8%D0%B9_%D0%98%D0%B2%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87_%D0%94%D0%BE%D0%BD%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B9">Дмитрия Донского</a> и ордынским войском <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9C%D0%B0%D0%BC%D0%B0%D0%B9">хана Мамая</a>,
с огромным количеством жертв, сыгравшему поворотную роль в русской истории,
и позднее названному <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%B1%D0%B8%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%B0">Куликовской битвой</a>.
Несмотря на то, что сам факт массового кровопролития не вызывает сомнений среди историков,
убедительно доказать, где именно это произошло, до сих пор
<a href="https://histrf.ru/read/articles/zagadki-kulikova-polya">проблематично</a>.</p>

<p>Действительно, как можно восстановить координаты поля,
на котором случилась кровавая сеча шесть веков тому назад? Где оно, <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BE_%D0%BF%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B5">поле</a> это?
Наверное, можно снова попытаться опереться на воспоминания “итальянцев-очевидцев”,
но в то время не было ни атласов автомобильных дорог, ни Google Maps,
да и параллели с меридианами еще не придумали. Даже если у битвы были очевидцы
владеющие письмом, могли бы они описать координаты места так,
чтобы сегодня их можно было бы найти на Яндекс Картах?</p>

<p><img src="/images/2024/04/zadonshina.png" style="width:100%;" /></p>

<p>Умением письма кое-кто тогда как раз владел. Некто Софоний Рязанец.
Он написал книгу <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%97%D0%B0%D0%B4%D0%BE%D0%BD%D1%89%D0%B8%D0%BD%D0%B0">Задонщина</a>,
как <a href="http://lib2.pushkinskijdom.ru/Media/Default/PDF/TODRL/12_tom/Nazarevskii/Nazarevskii.pdf">считается</a>, еще при жизни Дмитрия, в которой
<a href="http://drevne-rus-lit.niv.ru/drevne-rus-lit/text/zadonschina/zadonschina-original.htm">рассказал</a>
о месте встречи православного князя с татарским темником
следующее: “<span class="ponomar">проли́тсѧ крóви наречьке напрѧде</span>” где-то
“<span class="ponomar">между дóном и́ непрóм</span>” (на фото <a href="https://lib-fond.ru/lib-rgb/310/f-310-632/#image-169">Ундольский список</a>, страница 185, выделение мое).
Считается, что Софоний — наиболее достоверный свидетель тех событий, а значит
нужно искать на карте упомяную речку, где-то рядом будет и поле.
Вот только карты Руси XIV века с названиями мелких рек у нас нет.</p>

<p>А если бы такая карта была, я бы искал речку “Напряду”, где-то между
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%94%D0%BE%D0%BD">Доном</a> и <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%94%D0%BD%D0%B5%D0%BF%D1%80">Днепром</a>.
Однако, <a href="http://www.drevne.ru/lib/zadon_o.htm">в переводе</a>
почему-то эта фраза звучит так: “пролится крови на речьке Непрядве!”.
Как именно историки из “<span class="ponomar">напрѧда</span>” сделали “Непрядва”, мне сложно судить.
Очевидно, что такой перевод вносит некоторую погрешность в ход
дальнейшего расследования по нахождению места проведения битвы.
Однако, это лингвистическое допущение ничуть не смутило <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9D%D0%B5%D1%87%D0%B0%D0%B5%D0%B2,_%D0%A1%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BF%D0%B0%D0%BD_%D0%94%D0%BC%D0%B8%D1%82%D1%80%D0%B8%D0%B5%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Степана Нечаева</a>, который
в 1848 году обнаружил речку <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9D%D0%B5%D0%BF%D1%80%D1%8F%D0%B4%D0%B2%D0%B0">Непрядву</a> на землях своего имения, предложил
называть одно из своих полей <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BE_%D0%BF%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B5">Куликовым</a>, и стал собирать средства на <a href="https://kulpole.ru/places/memorial-na-krasnom-holme">памятник</a>.
Ему наверняка позавидовал, например, владелец речки <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9D%D0%B0%D0%B2%D0%BB%D1%8F_(%D0%91%D1%80%D1%8F%D0%BD%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%BE%D0%B1%D0%BB%D0%B0%D1%81%D1%82%D1%8C)">Навля</a> (Брянская область),
тоже подходящей названием под древнюю летопись, но инициатива уже была перехвачена.</p>

<p>Почти полтора века эта версия многих устраивала, до тех пор пока уже в наше время
математик <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A4%D0%BE%D0%BC%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%BA%D0%BE,_%D0%90%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%B9_%D0%A2%D0%B8%D0%BC%D0%BE%D1%84%D0%B5%D0%B5%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Анатолий Фоменко</a> с коллегами, в рамках работы над
<a href="https://chronologia.org/">Новой Хрологией</a>,
не <a href="https://chronologia.org/seven4_1/0601.html">предложили</a> перенести Куликово поле в центр нынешней Москвы, аргументируя это в основном
1) большей целесообразностью, с военной точки зрения, такого расположения в те времена,
2) почти полной <a href="https://www.ras.ru/digest/showdnews.aspx?id=44e0aa5d-b0d0-47fa-af88-a791b39f0598&amp;print=1">бесплодностью</a>
раскопков в имении Нечаева,
3) множественными захоронениями погибших воинов,
<a href="https://govoritmoskva.ru/news/120432/">обнаруженными</a> на территории Сретенки (район Москвы)
и
4) обнаружением практически всех географических названий (а их много!),
упоминаемых в источниках по Куликовской битве, на территории Москвы.
Например, по их мнению, речка в Москве, известная нам сегодня под именем
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9D%D0%B0%D0%BF%D1%80%D1%83%D0%B4%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%8F">Напрудная</a>, и есть та самая речка “<span class="ponomar">Напрѧда</span>”.</p>

<p>Можно сказать, что и версия Нечаева и версия Фоменко или одинаково достоверны
или одинаково недостоверны: и в том и в другом случае
оригинальное название реки не соответствует ее современному названию.
Однако, на мой взгляд, противоречий в версии Нечаева больше, хотя бы
потому, что раскопки не дали никаких значимых результатов.
Однако, историческое научное сообщество решило не воспринимать команду Фоменко
всерьез и даже слова его версии на суде истории не давать.
Например, русскоязычные страницы Wikipedia, посвященные <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%B1%D0%B8%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%B0">Куликовой битве</a> и
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BE_%D0%BF%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%B5">Куликовому полю</a> не упоминают Новую Хронологию вообще.</p>

<p>Сейчас речь не о том, где на самом деле находится Куликово поле. Меня, да и вас,
уважаемые читатели, это напрямую никак не касается, и
установление истины жизнь нашу никак не изменит.
Однако, задумайтесь, в развитом ли обществе мы живем, если альтернативные версии исторических
событий не имеют права на голос в “суде”? И дело даже не в государстве, не в Wikipedia,
не в учебниках истории. Дело в нас с вами. Способны ли мы беспристрастно
анализировать работы историков, критиковать их, спорить с ними, опровергать
их версии, но при этом уважать их? Уважать их так, как справедливый судья в равной мере
уважает как прокурора, так и адвоката. Или в нашей голове есть место
только для одного “канонического” Куликова поля?</p>

<p>Позвольте закончить свою мысль одной поучительной историей.
Несколько месяцев назад мне повезло иметь возможность пообщаться с
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ijy8_3efUuo">Анатолием Тимофеевичем Фоменко</a> и
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4-9MmyBP7gA">Глебом Владимировичем Носовским</a> на своем
YouTube канале, в формате интервью. Мы говорили в основном о <a href="https://chronologia.org/">Новой Хронологии</a>,
о их взгляде на историю и о сложностях, с которыми сталкиваются
авторы альтернативных взглядов на нее. Через некоторое время после публикации обоих видео роликов
я пригласил на интервью другого ученого, доктора технических наук, и получил
отказ. Привожу его полностью:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2024/04/refusal.png" style="width:100%; border: 1px solid gray;" /></p>

<p>Мне было стыдно читать это письмо. Стыдно за наших ученых.</p>

<p>У меня все.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="конспирология" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Великая битва на Куликовом поле произошла в 1380-м году, до сих пор точно не известно, где именно, это случилось, но альтернативные версии категорически отвергаются. Почему?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/04/peresvet-i-chelubej.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/04/peresvet-i-chelubej.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ping Me, Please!</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/04/01/ping-me-please.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ping Me, Please!" /><published>2024-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/04/01/ping-me-please</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/04/01/ping-me-please.html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a big difference between distributed and collocated teams: the
communication in distributed teams is asynchronous, which essentially
means that when you ask something, a response doesn’t arrive
immediately. Moreover, it may never arrive. This can be very
uncomfortable for those who are used to the office work setup, where
most communications are synchronous: any question is answered
immediately, one way or another. In open-source repositories,
everything is asynchronous. Here is a simple rule that may help you
decrease the level of frustration in GitHub projects: ping them every
time you need an answer or attention to be paid to your code.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="10th &amp; Wolf (2006) by Bobby Moresco" src="/images/2024/04/10th-and-wolf.jpg" longdesc="#4569e6d3" /><figcaption id="4569e6d3">10th &amp; Wolf (2006) by Bobby Moresco</figcaption></figure>

<p>There are four basic scenarios:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>You submitted a <em>new issue</em>.
Post a message asking the project architect to pay attention.
Otherwise, the owner of the backlog may miss your issue, and it will not be resolved for a long time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You sent a <em>new pull request</em>.
Post a message right in the PR, asking the architect to review it.
Otherwise, the architect may simply miss the pull request, and it will stay in the “waiting for review” state for a long time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You made <em>changes</em> in a pull request after code reviewers asked you.
Post a message asking them to look at your code again.
Otherwise, they may never see the changes you just made.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You post any <em>message</em> in an issue or a pull request.
<a href="/2020/07/29/open-source-etiquette.html">Start it</a> with the nickname of the person you are talking to.
Otherwise, the person who should help you may not receive a notification about your message, and it will be missed.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Also, listen to what Ben Batler from GitHub <a href="https://ben.balter.com/2014/11/06/rules-of-communicating-at-github/">said once</a>:
You essentially <em>never</em> “walk over” to a coworker’s desk, virtual or otherwise.
Whenever possible, prefer issues and chat over “just in time” communications.
Simply put, don’t text me in Telegram.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="mood" /><category term="oss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Distributed teams communicate asynchronously, causing delays in responses; frequent pinging can alleviate frustration in open-source projects.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/04/10th-and-wolf.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/04/10th-and-wolf.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Research Flow</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/02/06/research-flow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Flow" /><published>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/02/06/research-flow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/02/06/research-flow.html"><![CDATA[<p>Say, you are a student, and I’m your <a href="/2021/12/01/teaching.html">teacher</a>. 
Your task is to conduct 
an experiment or a study and then write a research paper about it. 
You can do it on your own and then present me with the results in the end. 
Sometimes it may work, but most probably it won’t. I will have many comments, 
suggestions, and plain simple disagreements with your research questions, results, 
or conclusions. Just like in software engineering, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model">Waterfall</a> approach 
is not an effective one. Instead, an <em>incremental and iterative</em> workflow 
may yield way better results: you take a small step forward, 
we discuss it, you rewrite, we agree, and you take the next step. 
The ultimate objective is to write a paper that will be published in 
a good journal or presented at a <a href="/2021/04/14/how-we-organized-iccq.html">decent conference</a>. 
Well, yes, a passing grade is also an objective.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Республика Шкид (1966) by Геннадий Полока" src="/images/2024/02/respublica-shkid.jpg" longdesc="#0f65f369" /><figcaption id="0f65f369">Республика Шкид (1966) by Геннадий Полока</figcaption></figure>

<p>Since the goal is a research paper, your first step is to create 
a skeleton of it in LaTeX. If you don’t know LaTeX yet, 
read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/LaTeX-Document-Preparation-System-2nd/dp/0201529831"><em>LaTeX: A Document Preparation System</em></a> 
by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie_Lamport">Leslie Lamport</a> (just 242 pages). 
If you think you already know LaTeX, 
read <a href="https://yegor256.github.io/latex-best-practices/main.pdf">this short list of its best practices</a> 
and <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-1-4471-6639-9"><em>Writing for Computer Science</em></a> 
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=uEHvqE8AAAAJ">Justin Zobel</a> (just 284 pages).</p>

<p>Now, create a document in <a href="https://overleaf.com">Overleaf</a>, 
and <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/learn/how-to/Sharing_a_project#Link_sharing">share a link</a> 
with me so that I can also edit the project. Use one of the following templates
(you should also <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/learn/how-to/Using_bibliographies_on_Overleaf">create</a>
an empty <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.bib</code> file too):
<a href="https://gist.github.com/yegor256/aa6215039cf687e4353c61385f23dd6c">ACM</a> (preferred),
<a href="https://gist.github.com/yegor256/58b289432d9ca13a6fd5946c77d8bd48">IEEE</a>,
and
<a href="https://gist.github.com/yegor256/905c0a1eac18eb6839a192b37f0816e4">Springer</a>.</p>

<p>Now, you are ready to begin your research incrementally, 
and I will review each step in the following order:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Research Questions</li>
  <li>Research Method — <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Preliminary Experiments</li>
  <li>Related Work — <a href="/2023/09/29/how-to-write-related-work-section.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Results — <a href="/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Limitations</li>
  <li>Discussion — <a href="/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Conclusion</li>
  <li>Introduction — <a href="/2022/08/24/research-paper-template.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Abstract</li>
  <li>Title</li>
</ol>

<p>Each step produces a few new paragraphs in the LaTeX document. 
In <a href="/2022/08/24/research-paper-template.html">this blog post</a>, 
you can find recommendations for each of the steps. I strongly advise against 
moving on to the next step unless the previous one is discussed and approved. 
Doing so may result in greater frustration on your part when you’ve 
written almost the entire paper, and we both realize that the 
whole piece must be rewritten, and experiments must be redone.</p>

<p>Before we start, please put a date on each of the steps mentioned above and send 
me the entire work plan. It’s better to meet every milestone as a disciplined student; 
otherwise, the risk of failure will be larger.</p>

<p>I believe that you, the reader of this blog post, are an honest and motivated 
student who not only cares about achieving a passing grade but also 
values contributing to computer science. However, not every student fits this description. 
Surprisingly, some may lack motivation or diligence. To prioritize the enthusiastic 
and dedicated students who require most of my attention, I may halt a research 
project when I discern a lack of genuine commitment. The use of 
<a href="/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt.html">ChatGPT</a>, 
plagiarism, and negligence may lead to an unfavorable assessment of your work. 
I strongly advise avoiding them.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a highly simplified description of a straightforward research workflow that I employ with my students in their research courses and diploma projects.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/02/respublica-shkid.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/02/respublica-shkid.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I can’t speak</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/01/03/not-able-to-speak.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I can’t speak" /><published>2024-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/01/03/not-able-to-speak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/01/03/not-able-to-speak.html"><![CDATA[<p>Уже несколько лет мы проводим в России <a href="https://www.iccq.ru/">научную конференцию</a>, 
приглашая в ее программный комитет ученых со всего мира. 
Последние два года, 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A1%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%BA%D1%86%D0%B8%D0%B8_%D0%B2_%D1%81%D0%B2%D1%8F%D0%B7%D0%B8_%D1%81%D0%BE_%D0%B2%D1%82%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B6%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B5%D0%BC_%D0%A0%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%81%D0%B8%D0%B8_%D0%BD%D0%B0_%D0%A3%D0%BA%D1%80%D0%B0%D0%B8%D0%BD%D1%83">по понятным причинам</a>, 
отказов много, особенно от западноевропейских ученых. Однако,
интересно вот что: если раньше отказы содержали субъективный негатив вроде 
“I don’t want to participate in a Russian conference” (я <em>не хочу</em> участвовать в российской конференции), 
то последнее время они все звучат примерно так: “I can’t speak at your event” (я <em>не могу</em> выступать у вас на мероприятии).
При всем уважении к драматизму ситуации, мне все же интересно, понимают ли уважаемые ученые, 
что те свободы, которыми так гордится европейская цивилизация, несовместимы с выражением “I can’t speak”,
особенно из уст людей науки?</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="BBC" src="/images/2024/01/silence.jpg" longdesc="#114aeb82" /><figcaption id="114aeb82">BBC</figcaption></figure>

<p>Последнее письмо я получил вчера:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2024/01/letter.png" alt="letter" /></p>

<p>И таких писем много, все в подобном стиле: я, мол, и рад бы, да не пускают,
мешают, ограничивают и вовсе запрещают. Вот еще одно:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2024/01/letter2.png" alt="letter" /></p>

<p>И это пишут не торговцы подержанными автомобилями, которым не разрешают
провозить через границу старые тойоты. Это пишут ученые, многие из которых помнят и 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%91%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BD%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B0">Берлинскую стену</a>,
и 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9F%D1%80%D0%B0%D0%B6%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%B2%D0%B5%D1%81%D0%BD%D0%B0">Пражскую весну</a>.
Они понимают, что такое свобода слова. Не могут не понимать.</p>

<p>Многие из них наверняка помнят цензуру времен <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A5%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B4%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%B2%D0%BE%D0%B9%D0%BD%D0%B0">Холодной войны</a>, 
когда каждую статью, перед тем как опубликовать
на конференции в лагере идеологического противника, нужно было согласовывать с 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A6%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B7%D1%83%D1%80%D0%B0_%D0%B2_%D0%A1%D0%A1%D0%A1%D0%A0">соответствующими органами</a>.
Однако, даже во времена 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%90%D0%BD%D0%B4%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%BF%D0%BE%D0%B2,_%D0%AE%D1%80%D0%B8%D0%B9_%D0%92%D0%BB%D0%B0%D0%B4%D0%B8%D0%BC%D0%B8%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B8%D1%87">Андропова</a> 
нельзя было представить, чтобы всем без разбора ученым было запрещено 
публиковать свои статьи и выступать на всех конференциях в стране “врага”.</p>

<p>Ученые всегда, даже во времена 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D0%B0%D1%80%D0%B8%D0%B1%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B9_%D0%BA%D1%80%D0%B8%D0%B7%D0%B8%D1%81">Карибского кризиса</a>, 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%90%D1%84%D0%B3%D0%B0%D0%BD%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%B2%D0%BE%D0%B9%D0%BD%D0%B0_(1979%E2%80%941989)">Афганского конфликта</a>, 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%92%D0%BE%D0%B9%D0%BD%D0%B0_%D0%B2%D0%BE_%D0%92%D1%8C%D0%B5%D1%82%D0%BD%D0%B0%D0%BC%D0%B5">Вьетнамской</a> и 
<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B5%D0%B9%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B0%D1%8F_%D0%B2%D0%BE%D0%B9%D0%BD%D0%B0">Корейских</a> войн,
были выше политики. Например, в 1977-м году в Новосибирске <a href="http://ershov.iis.nsk.su/ru/node/793556">состоялась</a> 
конференция <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Federation_for_Information_Processing">IFIP</a> 
посвященная “Построению качественного программного обеспечения”, на которой выступали (очно!)
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Parnas">David Parnas</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara_Liskov">Barbara Liskov</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Hoare">Tony Hoare</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edsger_W._Dijkstra">Edsger Dijkstra</a>
и
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_G._Neumann">Peter Neumann</a>.
И все это на фоне куда более жесткого идеологического противостояния, чем сейчас.</p>

<p>По всей видимости, в те времена люди у власти понимали, что наука и техника — это 
наше общее, всего человечества, движение вперед, а пули и бомбы — назад.
Видимо, они понимали, что изоляция ученых вредит сразу обеим сторонам — и тем, кого изолируют, 
и тем, кто изолирует, автоматически оказываясь в изоляции. Очень жаль, что люди власти в современной Европе
этого не понимают.</p>

<p>Более же всего тревожит молчаливая покорность ученых, которые “can’t speak”,
и которые наверняка понимают, к чему их и нас всех это приведет.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="свобода" /><category term="америка" /><category term="демократия" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[То, что западноевропейским ученым запрещают выступать на конференциях в России безусловно огорчает, но более всего настораживает их на это реакция.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/01/silence.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/01/silence.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Defend Me Against ChatGPT</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Defend Me Against ChatGPT" /><published>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt.html"><![CDATA[<p>I do enjoy <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ChatGPT">ChatGPT</a> a lot. 
The blog post you’re reading now was written by me and
then given to ChatGPT to fix its grammar and polish the writing style. Until
recently, since 2014, when I wrote my <a href="/2014/04/06/introduction.html">first blog post</a>, 
I used the service of a
few proofreaders, who charged me $20-40 per hour to rewrite 
<a href="/contents.html">all of my 350+ texts</a>. 
Now, I pay a few dollars a month to <a href="https://openai.com/">OpenAI</a>. However, while the value of
this generative AI is obvious, I also experience serious harm from ChatGPT,
especially when reading papers written by my students with its help.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Terminator (1984) by James Cameron" src="/images/2023/12/terminator.jpg" longdesc="#4a0c411e" /><figcaption id="4a0c411e">Terminator (1984) by James Cameron</figcaption></figure>

<p>Should students be allowed to use ChatGPT when they write their coursework,
diplomas, and research papers?
<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03507-3">Nature</a>,
<a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/teachers-ai-classroom-schools-678d7d84">The Wall Street Journal</a>,
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/02/02/learning/students-chatgpt.html">The New York Times</a>, 
and
<a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/04/06/1071059/chatgpt-change-not-destroy-education-openai/">MIT Technology Review</a>
believe that despite all the risks, we have no other choice: students will use
it, no matter what teachers think about it.</p>

<aside class="quote">Most of them will never read what the robot wrote.
</aside>

<p>Indeed, why not? What’s wrong with letting kids write those boring documents
faster? Nothing, if we ignore the obvious threat: most of them will never read
what the robot wrote. They simply prompt a very short description of the task
and get back a full-blown piece of text with all the necessary bells and
whistles. Moreover, with the next prompt, the text can be made even more
academic, sophisticated, smart, and deep. The text, not the student.</p>

<p>But it’s not the threat I worry about. I’m much more concerned about the quality
of feedback teachers will provide to students equipped with ChatGPT or a
similar paper-writing robot. My relatively <a href="/2021/12/01/teaching.html">short experience</a> in teaching
(just <a href="/teaching.html">three years</a>) tells me that the biggest challenge in teaching is quickly
<em>dividing</em> students into smart+enthusiastic (20%) and 
<a href="https://www.gcu.edu/blog/teaching-school-administration/myth-unmotivated-students">unmotivated</a> (80%), before
the latter category entirely exhausts me, and I classify <em>all</em> students
as “pointless waste of time” and give everybody an “A” just to get rid of
them.</p>

<p>When students write papers by themselves, without the help of 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_artificial_intelligence">generative AI</a>,
they make mistakes that are easy to spot: the grammar is wrong, the structure
is messy, the logic of the discussion is weak, and so on. Lazy and/or
stupid students reveal themselves in the first round of paper review. I
can quickly understand who I’m dealing with and stop paying attention to them.
The students who are smart and enthusiastic <em>win</em>, because they get my entire
attention. The unmotivated ones <em>lose</em>, … but who cares.</p>

<aside class="quote">Now, it takes much more time for me to understand who is who.
</aside>

<p>However, with the help of ChatGPT, the situation changes dramatically. Now, the
papers I have to review <em>all</em> look <em>perfect</em>: the grammar is spotless, the
structure is solid, and the flow of thoughts is logical. In other words, the
unmotivated students now <em>look like</em> smart and enthusiastic ones, while they are
not. Now, it takes much more time for me to understand who is who. Sometimes I
can’t figure it out for weeks, especially if the teaching is remote and I don’t
see students but only communicate with them in chats or conference calls.</p>

<p>I keep wasting my time on students who don’t care. All they need from me is a
passing grade, but ChatGPT makes them <em>look like</em> promising talents who I should
invest my time in. In the end, the students who really need my time don’t get
it, … thanks to ChatGPT.</p>

<p>Thus, I see ChatGPT as a big threat to the education process and believe that
very soon, tools that <a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/blog/how-to-tell-chat-gpt-generated-text/">validate texts</a> 
for the presence of generative AI in them
will become powerful enough to <em>defend</em> me from ChatGPT.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="ai" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If students are permitted to use ChatGPT as a paper-writing aid, teachers must possess a tool to detect the presence of generative AI in their texts.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/terminator.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/terminator.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Review a Research Paper: Constructive Critique in Five Steps</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/17/how-to-review-research-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review a Research Paper: Constructive Critique in Five Steps" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/17/how-to-review-research-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/17/how-to-review-research-paper.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m helping <a href="/2021/04/14/how-we-organized-iccq.html">organize</a> 
the <a href="https://www.iccq.ru">ICCQ conference</a> this year for the fourth time, with the
in-cooperation support of the IEEE Computer Society. Based on this short-term
experience, I can assert that reviewing research papers is a skill that even some
reputable and experienced academicians either don’t possess or are too lazy to
apply. We often encounter sketchy, subjective, and disputable reviews that
don’t assist authors but only frustrate and discourage them. In this short blog
post, as an absolute amateur in the subject matter, I will try to summarize how
to review an academic research paper (thus mostly helping other newbies).</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Берегись автомобиля (1966) by Эльдар Рязанов" src="/images/2023/12/beregis-avtomobila.jpg" longdesc="#ed6a985f" /><figcaption id="ed6a985f">Берегись автомобиля (1966) by Эльдар Рязанов</figcaption></figure>

<p>Structure your review as a plain text of <em>five</em> paragraphs, 
each answering one question:</p>

<ol>
  <li>How did you understand the thesis of the paper?</li>
  <li>What are the positive points?</li>
  <li>What are the major inconsistencies?</li>
  <li>What are the minor mistakes?</li>
  <li>What’s next?</li>
</ol>

<p>First, provide a brief summary of the paper. The main purpose of this paragraph
is to ensure that you, the reviewer, have actually read the paper and
understood what it’s about. Such summarization helps build <em>rapport</em> between you
and the readers of your review—the authors of the paper, whom you intend to
criticize. The better your summary, the more they will respect your negative
points, taking them constructively.</p>

<p>Then, identify the <strong>positive points</strong> of the paper, again demonstrating that you
have read and appreciate it. Here is a cheat list of the most typical merits a
good research paper may have (most important at the top):</p>

<ul>
  <li>The idea is new and contributes significantly to the field.</li>
  <li>The research question(s) are clear, well-defined, and relevant.</li>
  <li>The method is robust, appropriate, and clearly described.</li>
  <li>The paper thoroughly reviews existing literature.</li>
  <li>The data found effectively supports the conclusions.</li>
  <li>The results are significant.</li>
  <li>The conclusion effectively summarizes the research.</li>
  <li>The paper is well-organized.</li>
  <li>The paper is well-written with clear and concise language.</li>
</ul>

<p>Next, highlight the <strong>major</strong> inconsistencies. This list of typical 
mistakes may help you (the most severe ones are at the top):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Certain parts of the paper are obvious <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plagiarism">plagiarism</a>.</li>
  <li>The purpose of the research is unclear.</li>
  <li>The need for this research in the field is not obvious.</li>
  <li>The research questions are not clearly defined.</li>
  <li>Literature review misses important related work.</li>
  <li>Conclusions are not fully supported by the data.</li>
  <li>Data is distorted or cherry-picked to fit a hypothesis.</li>
  <li>The viewpoints presented are biased and/or lack balance.</li>
  <li>Important details of the <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">research method</a> are missing.</li>
  <li>Not all limitations or threats to validity are identified.</li>
  <li>The <a href="/2022/08/24/research-paper-template.html">structure</a> is not coherent.</li>
  <li>Some statements are ambiguous.</li>
</ul>

<p>Then, mention <strong>minor</strong> mistakes. The difference between minor and major
problems is that a minor problem is not a “show stopper”: a paper with minor
mistakes but without major ones may be accepted for publication, while the
opposite is not true. A paper with major issues must be rejected with a
suggestion for rework by the authors. Here is a list of the most typical minor
issues:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The abstract is inadequate.</li>
  <li>Sources are misquoted or <a href="/2023/09/05/style-checker-for-bibtex-files.html">incorrectly cited</a>.</li>
  <li>The title of the article is inappropriate.</li>
  <li>There are grammatical errors, typos, and unclear language.</li>
</ul>

<p>Finally, conclude your review: what should be done <strong>next</strong>? Do you suggest
publishing the paper? Do you think the authors are moving in the right
direction? Should they continue working on this topic, or would it be better to
abandon it for something more meaningful? Be honest and sincere; don’t be
afraid of offending them: the review is <em>anonymous</em> anyway.</p>

<p>Obviously, I’m joking. It’s easy to offend an author, especially a young one.
Thus, as a good reviewer, you must understand your mission: the review you
provide should help the authors by <em>encouraging</em> and <em>educating</em> them. Making
them feel miserable is definitely not the purpose of the review, though it is
sometimes an unfortunate side effect. Try to minimize it.</p>

<hr />

<p>Here is a toy example:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>In their research, the authors claim that all programmers 
are lazy and selfish creatures, grounding their conclusion 
on a survey of 150 respondents.

Pros:
  - An important topic was addressed.
  - The reasoning is clear and concise.
  - The conclusion is very true.

Major cons:
  - Similar research done by Dean [1] is overlooked.
  - It's obvious that they are lazy; why another research?
  - Only Java programmers were interviewed.

Minor cons:
  - Typos and broken English here and there.
  - The font in most figures is too small.

Even though the subject of the research is important, 
I believe this paper is not yet ready for publication 
and requires significant rework.

[1] Dean et al., Programmers Are Super Lazy, 2022
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A review of a research paper may be structured in five sections in order to be most effective for the authors of the paper being reviewed.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/beregis-avtomobila.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/beregis-avtomobila.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Results and Discussion: Facts and Interpretation</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Results and Discussion: Facts and Interpretation" /><published>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html"><![CDATA[<p>Almost every <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empirical_research">empirical research</a> 
paper contains two essential sections: <em>Results</em>
and <em>Discussion</em>. The former presents the facts collected through the research
<a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">method</a>, 
while the latter interprets them to answer the research questions. When
interpreting the data, you must address the most obvious concerns that readers
may have. For example, in the Results section, you might state: “85% of
respondents refused to participate in our survey” (this is a <em>fact</em>). Then, in
the Discussion section, you might say: “We believe that programmers are
innately lazy and irresponsible” (this is an <em>interpretation</em>). You might also
add, “Perhaps not all of them were lazy, but just busy.” While the Results
section leaves no room for doubt, summarizing findings “as is,” the Discussion
section engages in an open <em>debate</em> with an imaginative reader.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Mulholland Drive (2001) by David Lynch" src="/images/2023/12/mulholland-drive.jpg" longdesc="#b621cf09" /><figcaption id="b621cf09">Mulholland Drive (2001) by David Lynch</figcaption></figure>

<p>In the <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">Method</a> section, 
you’ve already explained how you collected, processed, and analyzed the data. 
Now, in the <strong>Results</strong> section, you present the actual data collected and generated. 
The simpler the method of data representation, the better. Thus, in order of 
preference (with the last being your last choice):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Plain text</li>
  <li>Lists (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\begin{itemize}</code>)</li>
  <li>Table (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\begin{tabular}</code>)</li>
  <li>Graphs and diagrams (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\begin{figure}</code>)</li>
</ul>

<p>If the data is too extensive to show in the paper, you can store it 
in a GitHub repository, create a <a href="https://zenodo.org">Zenodo</a> artifact,
and mention its address in the Results section. For example:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>\section{Results}

We contacted 135 programmers from three 
software companies: ACME Inc, Google, and
Amazon. We asked them kindly to answer
a short questionnaire of just 128 questions.
115 people refused, which is 85%.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Don’t forget to create a new GitHub repository with all the data that you collected
during the research: CSV files, scripts, survey answers, and so on. When
the repository is ready, publish it to Zenodo
(<a href="https://docs.github.com/en/repositories/archiving-a-github-repository/referencing-and-citing-content">this is how</a>),
and then cite it:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>The full list of those who refused, along with
their names and home addresses,
is published in Zenodo: \url{https://zenodo.com/...}.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>In the <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">Method</a> section, 
you posed several <em>Research Questions</em>. Now, in the <strong>Discussion</strong> section, 
you answer them using the data you’ve just presented in the Results. 
This is the time for an opinionated interpretation of the data: be brave and direct, yet careful.</p>

<p>When you’ve answered the Research Questions, you initiate a debate 
with your readers, imagining them asking difficult and important questions. 
The answers you provide are your speculation, imagination, improvisation, etc. 
Also, through the Q&amp;A format, you acknowledge the limitations of your 
research and suggest potential future research topics.</p>

<p>Consider these questions (re-phrase them for your own context):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Why are these results important?</li>
  <li>Why has no one discovered this before?</li>
  <li>Is it possible that we made a mistake?</li>
  <li>What data have we missed?</li>
  <li>How else could the data be interpreted?</li>
  <li>What’s next?</li>
</ul>

<p>I suggest dedicating exactly one paragraph per question, starting 
with a bold-faced formulation of it, followed by your answer to 
your imagined opponent. Here’s an example:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>\section{Discussion}

\textbf{RQ1: How many programmers are lazy?}
Since 85% of our respondents refused to complete
our short questionnaire, we strongly believe 
that most programmers are lazy.

\textbf{RQ2: Why are programmers lazy?}
Since the majority of programmers refused to complete
the 128-question questionnaire, we believe
they become lazy when confronted with a number
that is a power of two.

\textbf{Is it possible that programmers are 
just busy?} Yes, it's possible, but highly
unlikely, as \citet{x2019} previously found 
that programmers spend 90% of their office time 
reading jokes on the internet.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The more you overlook in the Discussion section, the greater the chance of your
paper being rejected. Reviewers are often knowledgeable individuals with many
years of experience in the field; they will certainly have concerns about your
Method, Results, and answers to the Research Questions. If you don’t address
these concerns explicitly in the Discussion section, they may think you are
either concealing the research’s weaknesses or are not astute enough to
recognize them. In either case, it could lead to a rejection of your paper.</p>

<hr />

<p>You may find inspiration in these papers 
(use <a href="https://scholar.google.com/">Google Scholar</a> to download their PDFs):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Zhaowei Zhang et al., <em>Diet Code Is Healthy: Simplifying Programs for Pre-trained Models of Code</em>, ESEC/FSE 2022</li>
  <li>Norman Peitek et al., <em>Correlates of Programmer Efficacy and Their Link to Experience: A Combined EEG and Eye-Tracking Study</em>, ESEC/FSE 2022</li>
  <li>Jennifer Bauer et al., <em>Indentation: Simply a Matter of Style or Support for Program Comprehension?</em>, ICPC 2019</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>These opinions might also be helpful:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://goldbio.com/articles/article/Guide-to-results-and-discussion-section">Guide to Writing the Results and Discussion Sections of a Scientific Article</a>
by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tyasning-kroemer/">Tyasning Kroemer</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://healthprofessions.udmercy.edu/academics/na/agm/htresult.htm">How to write the Results and Discussion</a>
by Michael P. Dosch</li>
  <li><a href="https://plos.org/resource/how-to-write-conclusions/">How to Write Discussions and Conclusions</a>
by PLOS</li>
  <li><a href="https://libguides.usc.edu/writingguide/discussion">The Discussion</a>
by USC Libraries</li>
  <li><a href="https://jivasquez.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/discussion.pdf">Fourteen Steps to Writing an Effective Discussion Section</a>
by Paul Kretchmer</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.sjsu.edu/writingcenter/docs/handouts/Discussion%20Section%20for%20Research%20Papers.pdf">Discussion Section for Research Papers</a>
by Rowan Dunton</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.uvm.edu/sites/default/files/Graduate-Writing-Center/GWC%20Guides/Genres/Science_Writing_Results_Discussion.pdf">Distinguishing between Results and Discussion</a>
by University of Vermont</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two very important sections of a research paper must present the data collected and the interpretations made.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/mulholland-drive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/mulholland-drive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Be Indirect in Your Research Questionnaire to Gain More Honesty</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/28/research-questionnaire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be Indirect in Your Research Questionnaire to Gain More Honesty" /><published>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/28/research-questionnaire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/28/research-questionnaire.html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say you are conducting research to discover programmers’ opinions about
their work environments: whether they appreciate their office spaces or not.
Preparing a survey with a few questions is essential. Their responses will
reveal their thoughts and feelings. After working with several student groups,
I’ve noticed a common mistake in questionnaire design—they are <em>too obvious</em> with
their questions, simply asking, “How do you feel about this?” There’s a more
effective approach.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Coffee and Cigarettes (2004) by Jim Jarmusch" src="/images/2023/11/coffee-and-cigarettes.jpg" longdesc="#c7fc0345" /><figcaption id="c7fc0345">Coffee and Cigarettes (2004) by Jim Jarmusch</figcaption></figure>

<p>Typically, to understand people’s thoughts and feelings, we might ask
directly, “What do you think and feel?” This is akin to a doctor
inquiring, “What is your disease? What kind of pill should I prescribe?” While
straightforward, this method suits a doctor less concerned with patient
recovery.</p>

<p>Asking directly also exposes the survey’s intent. Savvy respondents may realize
our research goals, potentially skewing results by conforming or sabotaging the
study. Some might claim they enjoy their work environment, while others might
express dissatisfaction. However, few will be entirely candid, feeling more
like researchers than participants.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of an ineffective survey structure:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Q1: Is your work environment comfortable?
  - Agree
  - Neutral
  - Disagree
Q2: Do you feel tired at the end of an office day?
  - Agree
  - Neutral
  - Disagree
Q3: Do you enjoy working in the office?
  - Agree
  - Neutral
  - Disagree
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A skilled doctor, rather than directly asking about diseases, inquires about
symptoms: “How often do you urinate?” or “Are you thirsty upon waking?”
Similarly, in empirical computer science studies, we can engage respondents
with hypothetical scenarios.</p>

<p>By asking respondents directly, we inadvertently shift our research
<em>responsibilities</em> onto them. Our role is to determine if they enjoy their office
space. We should observe their behavior, symptoms, and reactions to draw
conclusions. Simply asking, “Do you feel comfortable?” suggests a lazy or
inexperienced interviewer.
Responding to such a <em>generic</em> question, respondents will have to put together 
their entire experience of being in the office, analyze it, make some
conclusions, and then summarize them for us—this is the work we researchers have to do,
not our interviewees.</p>

<p>Consider this revised questionnaire:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Q4: With a looming strict deadline, where would you 
prefer to work on a critical software module?
  - At home
  - In a café
  - In the office
Q5: When did you last feel exhausted at the end of 
an office day?
  - A few days ago
  - A few weeks ago
  - Don't remember
Q6: How would you rate the office coffee 
machine's quality?
  - Excellent
  - It's OK
  - Poor
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The first two questions, Q4 and Q5, are <em>situational</em>, placing respondents in
specific scenarios. We then <em>interpret</em> their reactions to deduce answers to our
primary question: Do they like their work environments? This interpretation
<em>method</em> should be clarified in the research paper.</p>

<p>Question Q6, while not situational, is superior to Q1-Q3. It avoids asking
respondents to self-diagnose, subtly probing their opinions about office coffee
machines. The responses indirectly indicate their overall satisfaction with the
work environment.</p>

<p>In summary, avoid directly inquiring about illnesses; instead, ask about
symptoms to discreetly pursue your research objective. This approach elicits
more honest responses.</p>

<p>When the list of questions is ready, you can draw a table in your
research paper, listing all questions on a vertical axis and possible
answers on the horizontal one. Under each answer you mention the 
impact it makes to one of your research questions, for example:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>A<sub>1</sub></th>
      <th>A<sub>2</sub></th>
      <th>A<sub>3</sub></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Q<sub>4</sub>: With a looming strict deadline, where would you prefer to work on a critical software module?</td>
      <td>At home<br />RQ1<span class="down"></span></td>
      <td>In a café</td>
      <td>In the office<br />RQ1<span class="up"></span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Q<sub>5</sub>: When did you last feel exhausted at the end of an office day?</td>
      <td>A few days ago<br />RQ1<span class="down"></span></td>
      <td>A few weeks ago</td>
      <td>Don’t remember<br />RQ1<span class="up"></span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Q<sub>6</sub>: How would you rate the office coffee machine’s quality?</td>
      <td>Excellent<br />RQ1<span class="up"></span></td>
      <td>It’s OK</td>
      <td>Poor<br />RQ1<span class="down"></span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This table clearly explains to readers of your research, why did you
ask these questions and how the responses provided by the 
respondents helped you answer your research questions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When conducting a survey to ascertain people's feelings about a topic, it is more effective to use indirect questioning.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/11/coffee-and-cigarettes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/11/coffee-and-cigarettes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>