<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-07T01:15:38+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/rss.xml</id><title type="html">Yegor Bugayenko</title><subtitle>Yegor Bugayenko</subtitle><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Research Flow</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/02/06/research-flow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Flow" /><published>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2024/02/06/research-flow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2024/02/06/research-flow.html"><![CDATA[<p>Say, you are a student, and I’m your <a href="/2021/12/01/teaching.html">teacher</a>. 
Your task is to conduct 
an experiment or a study and then write a research paper about it. 
You can do it on your own and then present me with the results in the end. 
Sometimes it may work, but most probably it won’t. I will have many comments, 
suggestions, and plain simple disagreements with your research questions, results, 
or conclusions. Just like in software engineering, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model">Waterfall</a> approach 
is not an effective one. Instead, an <em>incremental and iterative</em> workflow 
may yield way better results: you take a small step forward, 
we discuss it, you rewrite, we agree, and you take the next step. 
The ultimate objective is to write a paper that will be published in 
a good journal or presented at a <a href="/2021/04/14/how-we-organized-iccq.html">decent conference</a>. 
Well, yes, a passing grade is also an objective.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Республика Шкид (1966) by Геннадий Полока" src="/images/2024/02/respublica-shkid.jpg" longdesc="#0f65f369" /><figcaption id="0f65f369">Республика Шкид (1966) by Геннадий Полока</figcaption></figure>

<p>Since the goal is a research paper, your first step is to create 
a skeleton of it in LaTeX. If you don’t know LaTeX yet, 
read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/LaTeX-Document-Preparation-System-2nd/dp/0201529831"><em>LaTeX: A Document Preparation System</em></a> 
by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie_Lamport">Leslie Lamport</a> (just 242 pages). 
If you think you already know LaTeX, 
read <a href="https://yegor256.github.io/latex-best-practices/main.pdf">this short list of its best practices</a> 
and <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-1-4471-6639-9"><em>Writing for Computer Science</em></a> 
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=uEHvqE8AAAAJ">Justin Zobel</a> (just 284 pages).</p>

<p>Now, create a document in <a href="https://overleaf.com">Overleaf</a>, 
and <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/learn/how-to/Sharing_a_project#Link_sharing">share a link</a> 
with me so that I can also edit the project. Make your skeleton look like 
this (you should also <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/learn/how-to/Using_bibliographies_on_Overleaf">create</a> 
an empty <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.bib</code> file too):</p>

<div class="language-tex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">\documentclass</span><span class="na">[sigplan,nonacm,anonymous,review]</span><span class="p">{</span>acmart<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\usepackage</span><span class="na">[utf8]</span><span class="p">{</span>inputenc<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\usepackage</span><span class="p">{</span>natbib<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\title</span><span class="p">{</span>My article<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\author</span><span class="p">{</span>John Doe<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\orcid</span><span class="p">{</span>0000-0001-0000-0000<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\email</span><span class="p">{</span>your email<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\affiliation</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="k">\institution</span><span class="p">{</span>University<span class="p">}</span><span class="k">\city</span><span class="p">{</span>City<span class="p">}</span><span class="k">\country</span><span class="p">{</span>Country<span class="p">}}</span>
<span class="nt">\begin{abstract}</span>
This paper is about something new.
<span class="nt">\end{abstract}</span>
<span class="nt">\begin{document}</span>
<span class="k">\maketitle</span>
<span class="k">\section</span><span class="p">{</span>Introduction<span class="p">}</span>
Hello, world!
<span class="k">\bibliographystyle</span><span class="p">{</span>ACM-Reference-Format<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\bibliography</span><span class="p">{</span>main<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="nt">\end{document}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Now, you are ready to begin your research incrementally, 
and I will review each step in the following order:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Research Questions</li>
  <li>Research Method — <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Preliminary Experiments</li>
  <li>Related Work — <a href="/2023/09/29/how-to-write-related-work-section.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Results — <a href="/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Limitations</li>
  <li>Discussion — <a href="/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html">how to?</a></li>
  <li>Conclusion</li>
  <li>Introduction</li>
  <li>Abstract</li>
  <li>Title</li>
</ol>

<p>Each step produces a few new paragraphs in the LaTeX document. 
In <a href="/2022/08/24/research-paper-template.html">this blog post</a>, 
you can find recommendations for each of the steps. I strongly advise against 
moving on to the next step unless the previous one is discussed and approved. 
Doing so may result in greater frustration on your part when you’ve 
written almost the entire paper, and we both realize that the 
whole piece must be rewritten, and experiments must be redone.</p>

<p>Before we start, please put a date on each of the steps mentioned above and send 
me the entire work plan. It’s better to meet every milestone as a disciplined student; 
otherwise, the risk of failure will be larger.</p>

<p>I believe that you, the reader of this blog post, are an honest and motivated 
student who not only cares about achieving a passing grade but also 
values contributing to computer science. However, not every student fits this description. 
Surprisingly, some may lack motivation or diligence. To prioritize the enthusiastic 
and dedicated students who require most of my attention, I may halt a research 
project when I discern a lack of genuine commitment. The use of 
<a href="/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt.html">ChatGPT</a>, 
plagiarism, and negligence may lead to an unfavorable assessment of your work. 
I strongly advise avoiding them.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a highly simplified description of a straightforward research workflow that I employ with my students in their research courses and diploma projects.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/02/respublica-shkid.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2024/02/respublica-shkid.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Defend Me Against ChatGPT</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Defend Me Against ChatGPT" /><published>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/26/defend-me-against-chatgpt.html"><![CDATA[<p>I do enjoy <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ChatGPT">ChatGPT</a> a lot. 
The blog post you’re reading now was written by me and
then given to ChatGPT to fix its grammar and polish the writing style. Until
recently, since 2014, when I wrote my <a href="/2014/04/06/introduction.html">first blog post</a>, 
I used the service of a
few proofreaders, who charged me $20-40 per hour to rewrite 
<a href="/contents.html">all of my 350+ texts</a>. 
Now, I pay a few dollars a month to <a href="https://openai.com/">OpenAI</a>. However, while the value of
this generative AI is obvious, I also experience serious harm from ChatGPT,
especially when reading papers written by my students with its help.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Terminator (1984) by James Cameron" src="/images/2023/12/terminator.jpg" longdesc="#4a0c411e" /><figcaption id="4a0c411e">Terminator (1984) by James Cameron</figcaption></figure>

<p>Should students be allowed to use ChatGPT when they write their coursework,
diplomas, and research papers?
<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03507-3">Nature</a>,
<a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/teachers-ai-classroom-schools-678d7d84">The Wall Street Journal</a>,
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/02/02/learning/students-chatgpt.html">The New York Times</a>, 
and
<a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/04/06/1071059/chatgpt-change-not-destroy-education-openai/">MIT Technology Review</a>
believe that despite all the risks, we have no other choice: students will use
it, no matter what teachers think about it.</p>

<aside class="quote">Most of them will never read what the robot wrote.
</aside>

<p>Indeed, why not? What’s wrong with letting kids write those boring documents
faster? Nothing, if we ignore the obvious threat: most of them will never read
what the robot wrote. They simply prompt a very short description of the task
and get back a full-blown piece of text with all the necessary bells and
whistles. Moreover, with the next prompt, the text can be made even more
academic, sophisticated, smart, and deep. The text, not the student.</p>

<p>But it’s not the threat I worry about. I’m much more concerned about the quality
of feedback teachers will provide to students equipped with ChatGPT or a
similar paper-writing robot. My relatively <a href="/2021/12/01/teaching.html">short experience</a> in teaching
(just <a href="/teaching.html">three years</a>) tells me that the biggest challenge in teaching is quickly
<em>dividing</em> students into smart+enthusiastic (20%) and 
<a href="https://www.gcu.edu/blog/teaching-school-administration/myth-unmotivated-students">unmotivated</a> (80%), before
the latter category entirely exhausts me, and I classify <em>all</em> students
as “pointless waste of time” and give everybody an “A” just to get rid of
them.</p>

<p>When students write papers by themselves, without the help of 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_artificial_intelligence">generative AI</a>,
they make mistakes that are easy to spot: the grammar is wrong, the structure
is messy, the logic of the discussion is weak, and so on. Lazy and/or
stupid students reveal themselves in the first round of paper review. I
can quickly understand who I’m dealing with and stop paying attention to them.
The students who are smart and enthusiastic <em>win</em>, because they get my entire
attention. The unmotivated ones <em>lose</em>, … but who cares.</p>

<aside class="quote">Now, it takes much more time for me to understand who is who.
</aside>

<p>However, with the help of ChatGPT, the situation changes dramatically. Now, the
papers I have to review <em>all</em> look <em>perfect</em>: the grammar is spotless, the
structure is solid, and the flow of thoughts is logical. In other words, the
unmotivated students now <em>look like</em> smart and enthusiastic ones, while they are
not. Now, it takes much more time for me to understand who is who. Sometimes I
can’t figure it out for weeks, especially if the teaching is remote and I don’t
see students but only communicate with them in chats or conference calls.</p>

<p>I keep wasting my time on students who don’t care. All they need from me is a
passing grade, but ChatGPT makes them <em>look like</em> promising talents who I should
invest my time in. In the end, the students who really need my time don’t get
it, … thanks to ChatGPT.</p>

<p>Thus, I see ChatGPT as a big threat to the education process and believe that
very soon, tools that <a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/blog/how-to-tell-chat-gpt-generated-text/">validate texts</a> 
for the presence of generative AI in them
will become powerful enough to <em>defend</em> me from ChatGPT.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="ai" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If students are permitted to use ChatGPT as a paper-writing aid, teachers must possess a tool to detect the presence of generative AI in their texts.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/terminator.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/terminator.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Review a Research Paper: Constructive Critique in Five Steps</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/17/how-to-review-research-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review a Research Paper: Constructive Critique in Five Steps" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/17/how-to-review-research-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/17/how-to-review-research-paper.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m helping <a href="/2021/04/14/how-we-organized-iccq.html">organize</a> 
the <a href="https://www.iccq.ru">ICCQ conference</a> this year for the fourth time, with the
in-cooperation support of the IEEE Computer Society. Based on this short-term
experience, I can assert that reviewing research papers is a skill that even some
reputable and experienced academicians either don’t possess or are too lazy to
apply. We often encounter sketchy, subjective, and disputable reviews that
don’t assist authors but only frustrate and discourage them. In this short blog
post, as an absolute amateur in the subject matter, I will try to summarize how
to review an academic research paper (thus mostly helping other newbies).</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Берегись автомобиля (1966) by Эльдар Рязанов" src="/images/2023/12/beregis-avtomobila.jpg" longdesc="#ed6a985f" /><figcaption id="ed6a985f">Берегись автомобиля (1966) by Эльдар Рязанов</figcaption></figure>

<p>Structure your review as a plain text of <em>five</em> paragraphs, 
each answering one question:</p>

<ol>
  <li>How did you understand the thesis of the paper?</li>
  <li>What are the positive points?</li>
  <li>What are the major inconsistencies?</li>
  <li>What are the minor mistakes?</li>
  <li>What’s next?</li>
</ol>

<p>First, provide a brief summary of the paper. The main purpose of this paragraph
is to ensure that you, the reviewer, have actually read the paper and
understood what it’s about. Such summarization helps build <em>rapport</em> between you
and the readers of your review—the authors of the paper, whom you intend to
criticize. The better your summary, the more they will respect your negative
points, taking them constructively.</p>

<p>Then, identify the <strong>positive points</strong> of the paper, again demonstrating that you
have read and appreciate it. Here is a cheat list of the most typical merits a
good research paper may have (most important at the top):</p>

<ul>
  <li>The idea is new and contributes significantly to the field.</li>
  <li>The research question(s) are clear, well-defined, and relevant.</li>
  <li>The method is robust, appropriate, and clearly described.</li>
  <li>The paper thoroughly reviews existing literature.</li>
  <li>The data found effectively supports the conclusions.</li>
  <li>The results are significant.</li>
  <li>The conclusion effectively summarizes the research.</li>
  <li>The paper is well-organized.</li>
  <li>The paper is well-written with clear and concise language.</li>
</ul>

<p>Next, highlight the <strong>major</strong> inconsistencies. This list of typical 
mistakes may help you (the most severe ones are at the top):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Certain parts of the paper are obvious <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plagiarism">plagiarism</a>.</li>
  <li>The purpose of the research is unclear.</li>
  <li>The need for this research in the field is not obvious.</li>
  <li>The research questions are not clearly defined.</li>
  <li>Literature review misses important related work.</li>
  <li>Conclusions are not fully supported by the data.</li>
  <li>Data is distorted or cherry-picked to fit a hypothesis.</li>
  <li>The viewpoints presented are biased and/or lack balance.</li>
  <li>Important details of the <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">research method</a> are missing.</li>
  <li>Not all limitations or threats to validity are identified.</li>
  <li>The <a href="/2022/08/24/research-paper-template.html">structure</a> is not coherent.</li>
  <li>Some statements are ambiguous.</li>
</ul>

<p>Then, mention <strong>minor</strong> mistakes. The difference between minor and major
problems is that a minor problem is not a “show stopper”: a paper with minor
mistakes but without major ones may be accepted for publication, while the
opposite is not true. A paper with major issues must be rejected with a
suggestion for rework by the authors. Here is a list of the most typical minor
issues:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The abstract is inadequate.</li>
  <li>Sources are misquoted or <a href="/2023/09/05/style-checker-for-bibtex-files.html">incorrectly cited</a>.</li>
  <li>The title of the article is inappropriate.</li>
  <li>There are grammatical errors, typos, and unclear language.</li>
</ul>

<p>Finally, conclude your review: what should be done <strong>next</strong>? Do you suggest
publishing the paper? Do you think the authors are moving in the right
direction? Should they continue working on this topic, or would it be better to
abandon it for something more meaningful? Be honest and sincere; don’t be
afraid of offending them: the review is <em>anonymous</em> anyway.</p>

<p>Obviously, I’m joking. It’s easy to offend an author, especially a young one.
Thus, as a good reviewer, you must understand your mission: the review you
provide should help the authors by <em>encouraging</em> and <em>educating</em> them. Making
them feel miserable is definitely not the purpose of the review, though it is
sometimes an unfortunate side effect. Try to minimize it.</p>

<hr />

<p>Here is a toy example:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>In their research, the authors claim that all programmers 
are lazy and selfish creatures, grounding their conclusion 
on a survey of 150 respondents.

Pros:
  - An important topic was addressed.
  - The reasoning is clear and concise.
  - The conclusion is very true.

Major cons:
  - Similar research done by Dean [1] is overlooked.
  - It's obvious that they are lazy; why another research?
  - Only Java programmers were interviewed.

Minor cons:
  - Typos and broken English here and there.
  - The font in most figures is too small.

Even though the subject of the research is important, 
I believe this paper is not yet ready for publication 
and requires significant rework.

[1] Dean et al., Programmers Are Super Lazy, 2022
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A review of a research paper may be structured in five sections in order to be most effective for the authors of the paper being reviewed.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/beregis-avtomobila.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/beregis-avtomobila.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Results and Discussion: Facts and Interpretation</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Results and Discussion: Facts and Interpretation" /><published>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html"><![CDATA[<p>Almost every <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empirical_research">empirical research</a> 
paper contains two essential sections: <em>Results</em>
and <em>Discussion</em>. The former presents the facts collected through the research
<a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">method</a>, 
while the latter interprets them to answer the research questions. When
interpreting the data, you must address the most obvious concerns that readers
may have. For example, in the Results section, you might state: “85% of
respondents refused to participate in our survey” (this is a <em>fact</em>). Then, in
the Discussion section, you might say: “We believe that programmers are
innately lazy and irresponsible” (this is an <em>interpretation</em>). You might also
add, “Perhaps not all of them were lazy, but just busy.” While the Results
section leaves no room for doubt, summarizing findings “as is,” the Discussion
section engages in an open <em>debate</em> with an imaginative reader.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Mulholland Drive (2001) by David Lynch" src="/images/2023/12/mulholland-drive.jpg" longdesc="#b621cf09" /><figcaption id="b621cf09">Mulholland Drive (2001) by David Lynch</figcaption></figure>

<p>In the <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">Method</a> section, 
you’ve already explained how you collected, processed, and analyzed the data. 
Now, in the <strong>Results</strong> section, you present the actual data collected and generated. 
The simpler the method of data representation, the better. Thus, in order of 
preference (with the last being your last choice):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Plain text</li>
  <li>Lists (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\begin{itemize}</code>)</li>
  <li>Table (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\begin{tabular}</code>)</li>
  <li>Graphs and diagrams (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\begin{figure}</code>)</li>
</ul>

<p>If the data is too extensive to show in the paper, you can store it 
in a GitHub repository and mention its address in the Results section. For example:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>\section{Results}

We contacted 135 programmers from three 
software companies: ACME Inc, Google, and
Amazon. We asked them kindly to answer
a short questionnaire of just 128 questions.
115 people refused, which is 85%.
The full list of those who refused, along with 
their names and home addresses, 
is published in GitHub repository\footnote{
  \url{https://github.com/...}}.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>In the <a href="/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html">Method</a> section, 
you posed several <em>Research Questions</em>. Now, in the <strong>Discussion</strong> section, 
you answer them using the data you’ve just presented in the Results. 
This is the time for an opinionated interpretation of the data: be brave and direct, yet careful.</p>

<p>When you’ve answered the Research Questions, you initiate a debate 
with your readers, imagining them asking difficult and important questions. 
The answers you provide are your speculation, imagination, improvisation, etc. 
Also, through the Q&amp;A format, you acknowledge the limitations of your 
research and suggest potential future research topics.</p>

<p>Consider these questions (re-phrase them for your own context):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Why are these results important?</li>
  <li>Why has no one discovered this before?</li>
  <li>Is it possible that we made a mistake?</li>
  <li>How else could the data be interpreted?</li>
  <li>What’s next?</li>
</ul>

<p>I suggest dedicating exactly one paragraph per question, starting 
with a bold-faced formulation of it, followed by your answer to 
your imagined opponent. Here’s an example:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>\section{Discussion}

\textbf{RQ1: How many programmers are lazy?}
Since 85% of our respondents refused to complete
our short questionnaire, we strongly believe 
that most programmers are lazy.

\textbf{RQ2: Why are programmers lazy?}
Since the majority of programmers refused to complete
the 128-question questionnaire, we believe
they become lazy when confronted with a number
that is a power of two.

\textbf{Is it possible that programmers are 
just busy?} Yes, it's possible, but highly
unlikely, as \citet{x2019} previously found 
that programmers spend 90% of their office time 
reading jokes on the internet.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The more you overlook in the Discussion section, the greater the chance of your
paper being rejected. Reviewers are often knowledgeable individuals with many
years of experience in the field; they will certainly have concerns about your
Method, Results, and answers to the Research Questions. If you don’t address
these concerns explicitly in the Discussion section, they may think you are
either concealing the research’s weaknesses or are not astute enough to
recognize them. In either case, it could lead to a rejection of your paper.</p>

<hr />

<p>You may find inspiration in these papers 
(use <a href="https://scholar.google.com/">Google Scholar</a> to download their PDFs):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Zhaowei Zhang et al., <em>Diet Code Is Healthy: Simplifying Programs for Pre-trained Models of Code</em>, ESEC/FSE 2022</li>
  <li>Norman Peitek et al., <em>Correlates of Programmer Efficacy and Their Link to Experience: A Combined EEG and Eye-Tracking Study</em>, ESEC/FSE 2022</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>These opinions might also be helpful:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://goldbio.com/articles/article/Guide-to-results-and-discussion-section">Guide to Writing the Results and Discussion Sections of a Scientific Article</a>
by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tyasning-kroemer/">Tyasning Kroemer</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://healthprofessions.udmercy.edu/academics/na/agm/htresult.htm">How to write the Results and Discussion</a>
by Michael P. Dosch</li>
  <li><a href="https://plos.org/resource/how-to-write-conclusions/">How to Write Discussions and Conclusions</a>
by PLOS</li>
  <li><a href="https://libguides.usc.edu/writingguide/discussion">The Discussion</a>
by USC Libraries</li>
  <li><a href="https://jivasquez.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/discussion.pdf">Fourteen Steps to Writing an Effective Discussion Section</a>
by Paul Kretchmer</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.sjsu.edu/writingcenter/docs/handouts/Discussion%20Section%20for%20Research%20Papers.pdf">Discussion Section for Research Papers</a>
by Rowan Dunton</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.uvm.edu/sites/default/files/Graduate-Writing-Center/GWC%20Guides/Genres/Science_Writing_Results_Discussion.pdf">Distinguishing between Results and Discussion</a>
by University of Vermont</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two very important sections of a research paper must present the data collected and the interpretations made.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/mulholland-drive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/12/mulholland-drive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Be Indirect in Your Research Questionnaire to Gain More Honesty</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/28/research-questionnaire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be Indirect in Your Research Questionnaire to Gain More Honesty" /><published>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/28/research-questionnaire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/28/research-questionnaire.html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say you are conducting research to discover programmers’ opinions about
their work environments: whether they appreciate their office spaces or not.
Preparing a survey with a few questions is essential. Their responses will
reveal their thoughts and feelings. After working with several student groups,
I’ve noticed a common mistake in questionnaire design—they are <em>too obvious</em> with
their questions, simply asking, “How do you feel about this?” There’s a more
effective approach.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Coffee and Cigarettes (2004) by Jim Jarmusch" src="/images/2023/11/coffee-and-cigarettes.jpg" longdesc="#c7fc0345" /><figcaption id="c7fc0345">Coffee and Cigarettes (2004) by Jim Jarmusch</figcaption></figure>

<p>Typically, to understand people’s thoughts and feelings, we might ask
directly, “What do you think and feel?” This is akin to a doctor
inquiring, “What is your disease? What kind of pill should I prescribe?” While
straightforward, this method suits a doctor less concerned with patient
recovery.</p>

<p>Asking directly also exposes the survey’s intent. Savvy respondents may realize
our research goals, potentially skewing results by conforming or sabotaging the
study. Some might claim they enjoy their work environment, while others might
express dissatisfaction. However, few will be entirely candid, feeling more
like researchers than participants.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of an ineffective survey structure:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Q1: Is your work environment comfortable?
  - Agree
  - Neutral
  - Disagree
Q2: Do you feel tired at the end of an office day?
  - Agree
  - Neutral
  - Disagree
Q3: Do you enjoy working in the office?
  - Agree
  - Neutral
  - Disagree
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A skilled doctor, rather than directly asking about diseases, inquires about
symptoms: “How often do you urinate?” or “Are you thirsty upon waking?”
Similarly, in empirical computer science studies, we can engage respondents
with hypothetical scenarios.</p>

<p>By asking respondents directly, we inadvertently shift our research
<em>responsibilities</em> onto them. Our role is to determine if they enjoy their office
space. We should observe their behavior, symptoms, and reactions to draw
conclusions. Simply asking, “Do you feel comfortable?” suggests a lazy or
inexperienced interviewer.
Responding to such a <em>generic</em> question, respondents will have to put together 
their entire experience of being in the office, analyze it, make some
conclusions, and then summarize them for us—this is the work we researchers have to do,
not our interviewees.</p>

<p>Consider this revised questionnaire:</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Q4: With a looming strict deadline, where would you 
prefer to work on a critical software module?
  - At home
  - In a café
  - In the office
Q5: When did you last feel exhausted at the end of 
an office day?
  - A few days ago
  - A few weeks ago
  - Don't remember
Q6: How would you rate the office coffee 
machine's quality?
  - Excellent
  - It's OK
  - Poor
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The first two questions, Q4 and Q5, are <em>situational</em>, placing respondents in
specific scenarios. We then <em>interpret</em> their reactions to deduce answers to our
primary question: Do they like their work environments? This interpretation
<em>method</em> should be clarified in the research paper.</p>

<p>Question Q6, while not situational, is superior to Q1-Q3. It avoids asking
respondents to self-diagnose, subtly probing their opinions about office coffee
machines. The responses indirectly indicate their overall satisfaction with the
work environment.</p>

<p>In summary, avoid directly inquiring about illnesses; instead, ask about
symptoms to discreetly pursue your research objective. This approach elicits
more honest responses.</p>

<p>When the list of questions is ready, you can draw a table in your
research paper, listing all questions on a vertical axis and possible
answers on the horizontal one. Under each answer you mention the 
impact it makes to one of your research questions, for example:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>A<sub>1</sub></th>
      <th>A<sub>2</sub></th>
      <th>A<sub>3</sub></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Q<sub>4</sub>: With a looming strict deadline, where would you prefer to work on a critical software module?</td>
      <td>At home<br />RQ1<span class="down"></span></td>
      <td>In a café</td>
      <td>In the office<br />RQ1<span class="up"></span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Q<sub>5</sub>: When did you last feel exhausted at the end of an office day?</td>
      <td>A few days ago<br />RQ1<span class="down"></span></td>
      <td>A few weeks ago</td>
      <td>Don’t remember<br />RQ1<span class="up"></span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Q<sub>6</sub>: How would you rate the office coffee machine’s quality?</td>
      <td>Excellent<br />RQ1<span class="up"></span></td>
      <td>It’s OK</td>
      <td>Poor<br />RQ1<span class="down"></span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This table clearly explains to readers of your research, why did you
ask these questions and how the responses provided by the 
respondents helped you answer your research questions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When conducting a survey to ascertain people's feelings about a topic, it is more effective to use indirect questioning.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/11/coffee-and-cigarettes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/11/coffee-and-cigarettes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Avoid Soft Line Breaks Inside a Paragraph</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/22/avoid-line-breaks-inside-paragrap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoid Soft Line Breaks Inside a Paragraph" /><published>2023-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/22/avoid-line-breaks-inside-paragrap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/11/22/avoid-line-breaks-inside-paragrap.html"><![CDATA[<p>An email, a document, a research paper, a presentation, and even a JavaDoc code block consist of
<em>paragraphs</em>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paragraph">which are</a> 
“self-contained units of discourse in writing dealing with a particular point or idea.”
Visually, paragraphs are supposed to be separated by a vertical space that is a bit larger
than a vertical spacing between lines. To achieve this, for example, in HTML, we wrap paragraphs in the 
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;p&gt;</code> tag, while in LaTeX, we use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\par</code> or just an empty line between them. However, some people insert
what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Line_wrap_and_word_wrap">are called</a> 
“<em>soft line breaks</em>” inside paragraphs—this is a bad practice that I suggest you stay away from.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Prêt-à-Porter (1994) by Robert Altman" src="/images/2023/11/pret-a-porter.jpg" longdesc="#b23bf235" /><figcaption id="b23bf235">Prêt-à-Porter (1994) by Robert Altman</figcaption></figure>

<p>This is how a paragraph should look, in HTML (no soft breaks, just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;p&gt;</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;/p&gt;</code>):</p>

<p style="color: green; width: 80%; font-family: monospace; font-size: 80%; line-height: 1.2em;">
&lt;p&gt;Tyler gets me a job as a waiter, after<br /> 
that Tyler's pushing a gun in my mouth and <br />
saying, the first step to eternal life is you <br />
have to die. For a long time though, Tyler <br />
and I were best friends. People are always <br />
asking, did I know about Tyler Durden.&lt;/p&gt;
</p>

<p>This is how it would look with soft breaks (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;br/&gt;</code>) after each sentence:</p>

<p style="color: red; width: 80%; font-family: monospace; font-size: 80%; line-height: 1.2em;">
&lt;p&gt;Tyler gets me a job as a waiter, after <br />
that Tyler's pushing a gun in my mouth and <br />
saying, the first step to eternal life is you <br />
have to die.<b>&lt;br/&gt;</b> <br />
For a long time though, Tyler and I were best <br />
friends.<b>&lt;br/&gt;</b><br />
People are always asking, did I know about <br />
Tyler Durden.&lt;/p&gt;
</p>

<p>Don’t do this.</p>

<p>Let the software format paragraphs for you, deciding where their lines
must break to form new lines. By injecting linebreaks into the body of
a paragraph, you express distrust in the document formatting software,
be it an HTML browser, a LaTeX compiler, or a Javadoc generator. In the end,
it looks ugly, because we are <a href="/2019/05/21/dont-improvise.html">much worse designers</a> 
than the creators of LaTeX or browsers.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="mood" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explicit line breaks inside a paragraph is a very annoying typography mistake, which I strongly recommend to avoid.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/11/pret-a-porter.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/11/pret-a-porter.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Method Section: A Recipe for Research</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Method Section: A Recipe for Research" /><published>2023-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/10/11/method-of-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/10/11/method-of-research.html"><![CDATA[<p>Every empirical research paper must have a section titled “Method” (or “Methodology,” or “Study Design”). In this section, you describe what was done to obtain the data presented in the following “Results” section. You explain the <em>recipe</em>, which may be replicated later by another researcher, leading to the same (or very similar) results.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Underground (1995) by Emir Kusturica" src="/images/2023/10/underground.jpg" longdesc="#952f1bf5" /><figcaption id="952f1bf5">Underground (1995) by Emir Kusturica</figcaption></figure>

<p>The Method section is the essence of the research. Think of it as a recipe: you
tell the reader what ingredients you used, how you mixed them, and—most
importantly—why.</p>

<p>You start the section with a paragraph where you state the main <em>objective</em> of the
research, then break it down into a few 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Research_question"><em>research questions</em></a>.</p>

<p>Then, you explain the <em>procedures</em> of the method (strictly one procedure per paragraph). 
In each step, you either collected, combined, or generated data. First, you explain what
you did. Second, you highlight how your procedure contributed to one of the
research questions. Third, you justify your actions by providing strong enough
reasons for why you performed these specific manipulations with the data.</p>

<p>Here is a toy sample of the Method section:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>\section{Method}

The goal of this study is to understand whether 
cats love fruits. This leads to the following 
research questions:   
\begin{description}
\item[RQ1] What is a correlation between the color 
of a cat's fur and its passion for fruits? 
\item[RQ2] Which fruits are preferred by cats: 
bananas, apples, or marakujas?
\end{description}

First, we found 15 cats: 2 white, 3 black, 
and 10 of mixed color. It is important for RQ1 
that they are of different colors. We believe 
that 15 is enough because this is a toy research.

Second, we excluded 5 cats: those who were 
younger than one year old or older than 8 years 
old. This was motivated by RQ2; we believe that 
young and old cats may have difficulty cracking 
the hard cover of a marakuja.

Third, we gave our cats all three fruits mentioned 
in RQ2, left them for an hour, and observed their 
behavior. We believe one hour is enough for a hungry
cat to make a decision.

All cat owners agreed to have their cats 
participate in the study. 
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>At the end of the section, we mentioned that all participants in the experiment
provided informed consent—this is important if humans (or cats) are involved,
so don’t forget about it.</p>

<p>In the “Results” section, which follows the Method, you 
<a href="/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html">present</a> the data that
were collected, combined, or generated (without giving any opinion or
subjective interpretation of it!). Some of this data may have already been
mentioned in the Method section, but not the most important details. For
example, we’ve already said that we found 15 cats, but we didn’t provide their
names, ages, or breeds—this information goes into the Results, in the form of
a nicely formatted table. How much “results” to show in the Method and how much
in the Results is, I believe, a matter of taste.</p>

<p>In the “Discussion” section, which follows the Results, you 
<a href="/2023/12/11/results-and-discussion.html">engage in a dialogue</a>
with yourself, questioning the procedures of the Method. This is where
you are allowed to have an opinion about the data collected, combined, and
generated. For example, we may discuss whether the results of our research
are trustworthy enough, taking into account that we only analyzed the behavior
of just 15 cats, while in the Method, we were absolutely sure that we were doing
the right thing. In the Discussion, you play the opposite role by doubting
every single step of the Method, highlighting its weaknesses and limitations.</p>

<hr />

<p>You may find inspiration in these papers 
(use <a href="https://scholar.google.com/">Google Scholar</a> to download their PDFs):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Melina Vidoni, <em>Evaluating Unit Testing Practices in R Packages</em>, ICSE 2021</li>
  <li>Reem S. Alsuhaibani et al., <em>On the Naming of Methods: A Survey of Professional Developers</em>, ICSE 2021</li>
  <li>Anastasia Ruvimova et al., <em>An Exploratory Study of Productivity in Software Teams</em>, ICSE 2022</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>These opinions might also be helpful:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://research.com/research/how-to-write-research-methodology">How to Write Research Methodology</a>
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=kudrpNsAAAAJ">Imed Bouchrika</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SxKd66g7M1s">Writing the ‘Research Methods’…</a> (video)
by <a href="https://soc.appstate.edu/faculty-staff/david-russell-phd">David Russell</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jWPul_eifeU">How To Write Methodology…</a> (video)
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=MR45-AwAAAAJ">Marek Kiczkowiak</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6322175/">Formulation of Research Question</a>
by Simmi K. Ratan</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The essence of a research paper is the Method section, which may be easier to write if you follow a few simple principles.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/10/underground.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/10/underground.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Related Work: A Critical Taxonomy of Prior Art</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/29/how-to-write-related-work-section.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Related Work: A Critical Taxonomy of Prior Art" /><published>2023-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/29/how-to-write-related-work-section</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/29/how-to-write-related-work-section.html"><![CDATA[<p>In almost any research paper, it is mandatory to have a section titled “Related Work”
(<a href="https://english.stackexchange.com/questions/55898/related-work-or-related-works">or “Related Works”</a>), 
where you refer to the results previously obtained by other
authors or yourself. By including this section in your paper, you are not only paying
respect to those who laid the foundation for your results, but also motivating and guiding
your readers. Most of them may not be aware of existing studies or
the importance of the problem you are solving. You must put these guys into
<a href="/2018/10/16/dont-make-me-guess.html">context</a>.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="Mean Streets (1973) by Martin Scorsese" src="/images/2023/09/mean-streets.jpg" longdesc="#39399260" /><figcaption id="39399260">Mean Streets (1973) by Martin Scorsese</figcaption></figure>

<p>As far as I understand it, a well-crafted “Related Work” section should convey the following <em>message</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Not only you believe that the problem is important,</li>
  <li>Previous studies have either overlooked or failed to solve it, and</li>
  <li>Your research is not a mere replication of someone else’s work.</li>
</ul>

<p>Before diving in, let’s clarify that the “Related Work” section 
<a href="https://academia.stackexchange.com/questions/157842">is not</a> the place 
to explain foundational concepts like 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning">Deep Learning</a> or 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dataflow_architecture">Dataflow Architecture</a>. 
That’s what the “<a href="https://scientific-publishing.webshop.elsevier.com/manuscript-preparation/what-background-study-and-how-should-it-be-written/">Background</a>” section is for. 
In “Related Work,” it’s assumed that the reader is already familiar with the subject matter.</p>

<p>To effectively communicate the three-fold message, create a <em>taxonomy</em> of existing studies. 
In simple terms, classify them. For instance, if your paper focuses on a new type 
of cat food designed to extend feline longevity and improve happiness, 
your “Related Work” section might look like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>There are three categories of research related to our 
study: cat food, cat happiness, and cat lifespan.

Earlier studies [2, 13, 8] have suggested that 
cat food containing meat [21], potato [11], and 
fish [7] results in complaints in only 7.5% of all 
cases. However, no experiments have been conducted 
with food made from fruits.

The happiness of cats and other pets has been 
studied by Johnson [22] and Dickson [17]. They 
identified a strong correlation between the mood 
of a pet's owner and the mood of the pet. However, 
they did not investigate the effect of food on cat 
happiness.

It has been observed [15, 18] that cats live 
longer when they consume food with fewer carbohydrates 
and more protein. However, these experiments were 
conducted with cats living in only one city, which
limits the applicability of these studies.

To the best of our knowledge, the method of feeding 
cats with fruits to increase their happiness and 
prolong their lives has not been studied yet.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Note the use of the word “however” in the last sentence of each paragraph. 
It highlights gaps in existing research that your study aims to fill. 
The final paragraph confirms your awareness that your research is unique. 
While you might be mistaken, explicitly stating your unawareness would make it an honest mistake.</p>

<p>In this toy example, we’ve categorized all relevant prior work into 
three groups. We’ve cited key papers in each category and summarized 
their findings relevant to our study. We’ve also highlighted areas 
that our research will address, emphasizing its novelty.</p>

<p>When gathering references for the “Related Work” section, you’ll likely 
encounter many papers worth mentioning. How do you decide which to cite? 
Consider the following factors:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Relevance: The closer it is to your topic, the better.</li>
  <li>Citations: Opt for papers that are cited more frequently.</li>
  <li>Venue: Consult <a href="https://www.scimagojr.com/journalrank.php">journal rankings</a> and <a href="http://portal.core.edu.au/conf-ranks/">conference rankings</a> to choose the most reputable sources.</li>
</ul>

<p>Lastly, <a href="https://scholar.google.com">Google Scholar</a> is the best place
for finding prior work. If you can’t access a PDF version of a paper, try the Telegram bot: 
<a href="https://t.me/scihubbot">@scihubbot</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>These articles and books might also be helpful:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tBud5yewkkc&amp;t=19s">How to write a Related Work…</a> (video) 
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=cZ5pY9wAAAAJ">Simone Silvestrini</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rk_jgtdJOD0">Literature Review: Step by Step…</a> (video)
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=W03REUoAAAAJ">David Stuckler</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://slowsearching.blogspot.com/2014/11/a-formula-for-academic-papers-related.html">A Formula for Academic Papers: Related Work</a> 
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=F5Ik84MAAAAJ">Jaime Teevan</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lucalongo.eu/howtowritearesearchpaper.html">How to write a research paper in science</a> 
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=oBqRuY8AAAAJ">Luca Longo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://sites.umiacs.umd.edu/elm/2019/02/22/writing-the-literature-review/">Writing the Literature Review</a>
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=LoQXe24AAAAJ">Niklas Elmqvist</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://steveharoz.com/blog/2015/related-work-section/">Why I Don’t Write a “Related Work” Section</a>
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=OcKUn3gAAAAJ">Steve Haroz</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/165854.165934">How to get a paper accepted at OOPSLA</a> 
by Kent Beck et al.</li>
  <li><a href="https://lemire.me/blog/rules-to-write-a-good-research-paper/">Write good papers</a>
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=q1ja-G8AAAAJ">Daniel Lemire</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://cs.dartmouth.edu/~wjarosz/writing.md.html">Common mistakes in technical writing</a>
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=vrjL9p0AAAAJ">Wojciech Jarosz</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://spie.org/samples/9781510619142.pdf">How to Write a Good Scientific Paper</a>
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=kMsXV0oAAAAJ">Chris A. Mack</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-1-4471-6639-9">Writing for Computer Science</a> 
by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=uEHvqE8AAAAJ">Justin Zobel</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In every reseach paper, the "Related Work" section is one of the most important and probably the most difficult to write.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/09/mean-streets.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/09/mean-streets.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Ingredients of Tech Career</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/19/five-ingredients-career.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Ingredients of Tech Career" /><published>2023-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/19/five-ingredients-career</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/19/five-ingredients-career.html"><![CDATA[<p>A friend of mine recently asked me what five things he should do in order to
grow his technical career in a big company. He is not interested in being a big
manager, or a CEO. Rather, he wants to be a software expert, an architect, an
owner of a technology, and eventually a “Fellow.” I’m not sure I was qualified
to give such advice, but I did anyway. This is what I told him. Maybe this will
also work for you.</p>

<!--more-->

<figure class="jb_picture"><img itemprop="image" alt="8½ (1963) by Federico Fellini" src="/images/2023/09/eight-and-half.jpg" longdesc="#39678366" /><figcaption id="39678366">8½ (1963) by Federico Fellini</figcaption></figure>

<h2 id="boredom">Boredom</h2>

<p>Stay focused on one problem for many years. I literally mean
a “problem”—something that bothers people now but will stop bothering them
when you solve it. Ideally, first and foremost, it should bother you
personally. If you can’t specify in one sentence what the meaning of your
office life is—you don’t have a problem to solve. Find one.</p>

<p>A strong multi-year focus on one particular problem will most likely lead to a
rather boring office life. People around you will be switching projects,
accepting offers from crypto-startups, changing technologies, programming
languages, and teams. You, unlike them, will remain focused on one thing for
years and years. Imagine how boring it will look to them and to yourself. So be
it. Accept it.</p>

<p>Moreover, if you don’t see significant results (and you won’t for years!),
you’ll be tempted to switch to something else, where the outcomes seem more
promising. Don’t.</p>

<p>Even when you change companies, remain loyal to the problem you chose as “yours”
years ago. Don’t betray it. It’s yours. Your lifetime mission is to solve it.
Who cares which company you are in? A company is just a temporary sponsor of
your mission.</p>

<h2 id="enemies">Enemies</h2>

<p>The problem must be as monumental as finding a cure for cancer. Ensure it’s
bigger than your team, your company, and even your lifespan. The
word “ambitious” certainly fits: it must be an ambitious idea. How do you know
it’s big and ambitious enough? Count your enemies. If you have many of
them—which could include your bosses, colleagues, spouse, and, of course,
your haters on Twitter—you have a solid case. Conversely, if everyone loves
your idea and supports you, your challenge might not be big enough.</p>

<p>Think about it: If it is big enough, many people have already tried to solve it.
They failed. Naturally, they would love to see you fail too. If you don’t, it
could dent their self-respect. It’s basic psychology.</p>

<h2 id="patrons">Patrons</h2>

<p>The more enemies, the better! However, you should have a few allies. I’m
referring to high-level technical people, like a CTO, VP of Technology, Chief
Architect, or Fellow. They might not be technically competent in your
particular domain, but that doesn’t matter. Strive to establish an information
channel between you and them, and periodically share updates. Keep them
informed about your progress and occasionally seek their advice. They will
shield you from most of the attacks your enemies might launch.</p>

<h2 id="friends">Friends</h2>

<p>To clarify, it’s impossible to ascend in a human hierarchy on your own, no
matter how bright you are. You need a cadre of supporters within the
company—individuals who back you unconditionally. A few are sufficient. They
must be personally loyal to you. If you leave the company, they should follow
you without hesitation.</p>

<p>It would be ideal for all of these friends to be part of your team. However,
that’s not always feasible. Similarly, it would be wonderful if all these
friends were technically competent, but that’s not always the case. In
contrast, loyalty doesn’t often coincide with expertise. Having a friend who is
both loyal and intelligent is a luxury.</p>

<h2 id="students">Students</h2>

<p>Finally, maintain a connection with the younger generation that’s succeeding
us—students. Engage with them, learn from them, and ensure you understand
their needs and aspirations. They represent the industry’s future. If you treat
them right, they will work for you with enthusiasm unmatched by any other
employee.</p>

<p>Strengthening ties with the academic world will unquestionably reinforce your
position within your company.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="career" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is the recipe of success in a big technical organization? Aside from the usual butt-kissing, what may guarantee career growth?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/09/eight-and-half.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.yegor256.com/images/2023/09/eight-and-half.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bibcop: Style Checker for BibTeX</title><link href="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/05/style-checker-for-bibtex-files.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bibcop: Style Checker for BibTeX" /><published>2023-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/05/style-checker-for-bibtex-files</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yegor256.com/2023/09/05/style-checker-for-bibtex-files.html"><![CDATA[<p>Almost every document you may write in 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LaTeX">LaTeX</a> format will
have a list of references at the end. Most likely, you will
use <a href="https://www.ctan.org/pkg/bibtex">BibTeX</a> 
or <a href="https://www.ctan.org/pkg/biblatex">BibLaTeX</a> 
to print this list of references in a nicely formatted way.
It is also highly probable that your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.bib</code> file will contain
many typographic, stylistic, and logical mistakes. I’m fairly
certain that you won’t find the time to identify and correct them.
As a result, the “References” section in your paper may appear sloppy.
I suggest using the <a href="https://www.ctan.org/pkg/bibcop"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bibcop</code></a> 
package, which identifies mistakes in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.bib</code> file 
and auto-fixes some of them.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Here is a practical example. Let’s say, you want to 
cite a famous paper about transformers. First, you find it in
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/">Google Scholar</a> and click “Cite”:</p>

<figure class="picture"><img src="/images/2023/09/bibcop-scholar.png" style="width:600px;max-width:100%;" alt="picture" /></figure>

<p>Then, you put this “bib” item into your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.bib</code> file:</p>

<div class="language-java highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nd">@article</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">vaswani2017attention</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="n">title</span><span class="o">={</span><span class="nc">Attention</span> <span class="n">is</span> <span class="n">all</span> <span class="n">you</span> <span class="n">need</span><span class="o">},</span>
  <span class="n">author</span><span class="o">={</span><span class="nc">Vaswani</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Ashish</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="nc">Shazeer</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Noam</span> <span class="n">and</span> 
    <span class="nc">Parmar</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Niki</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="nc">Uszkoreit</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Jakob</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="nc">Jones</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Llion</span> <span class="n">and</span> 
    <span class="nc">Gomez</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Aidan</span> <span class="no">N</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="nc">Kaiser</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="o">{</span><span class="err">\</span><span class="no">L</span><span class="o">}</span><span class="n">ukasz</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="nc">Polosukhin</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">Illia</span><span class="o">},</span>
  <span class="n">journal</span><span class="o">={</span><span class="nc">Advances</span> <span class="n">in</span> <span class="n">neural</span> <span class="n">information</span> <span class="n">processing</span> <span class="n">systems</span><span class="o">},</span>
  <span class="n">volume</span><span class="o">={</span><span class="mi">30</span><span class="o">},</span>
  <span class="n">year</span><span class="o">={</span><span class="mi">2017</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="o">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Then, you write something like this in your paper:</p>

<div class="language-java highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="err">\</span><span class="n">documentclass</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">article</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">usepackage</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">maxbibnames</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">9</span><span class="o">]{</span><span class="n">biblatex</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">addbibresource</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">main</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">bib</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">begin</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">document</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="nc">Transformers</span><span class="o">~</span><span class="err">\</span><span class="n">cite</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">vaswani2017attention</span><span class="o">}</span> 
<span class="n">changed</span> <span class="n">everything</span><span class="o">!</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">printbibliography</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">end</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">document</span><span class="o">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This is what you will get:</p>

<figure class="picture"><img src="/images/2023/09/bibcop-before.png" style="width:600px;max-width:100%;" alt="picture" /></figure>

<p>Looks more or less fine. 
However, if you go to <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017">the website</a> 
of the publisher of this article, you will see that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The name of <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/">the journal</a> is typed with first letters capitalized in all major words,</li>
  <li>The title of the paper is also capitalized,</li>
  <li>The middle name of “Aidan N. Gomez” has a trailing dot.</li>
</ul>

<p>In other words, Google Scholar gave you the citation with a few typographic
mistakes. While not fatal, the quality of the “References” section 
can sometimes be seen as reflective of the quality of the paper as a whole. 
Simply put, negligence is not forgivable when dealing with information about other authors. 
We must be accurate down to every letter and every dot.</p>

<p>By including <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bibcop</code> package to the document, the problem may be solved.
First, you install it (I assume, you are using <a href="https://tug.org/texlive/">TeX Live</a>):</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>tlmgr <span class="nb">install </span>bibcop
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Then, you add this to your document, right before the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\addbibresource</code> command:</p>

<div class="language-java highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="o">...</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">usepackage</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">bibcop</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="err">\</span><span class="n">addbibresource</span><span class="o">{</span><span class="n">main</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">bib</span><span class="o">}</span>
<span class="o">...</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>When you compile the document, the following warnings will be printed
to the console, together with other logs:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Package bibcop Warning: A shortened name must have 
  a tailing dot in the 6th 'author', as in 'Knuth, Donald E.', 
  in the 'vaswani2017attention' entry.
Package bibcop Warning: All major words in the 'title' 
  must be capitalized, while the 2nd word 'is' is not, 
  in the 'vaswani2017attention' entry.
Package bibcop Warning: A mandatory 'doi' tag for '@article' 
  is missing among (author, journal, title, volume, year), 
  in the 'vaswani2017attention' entry.
Package bibcop Warning: The 'title' must be wrapped 
  in double curled brackets, 
  in the 'vaswani2017attention' entry.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>You fix them all in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.bib</code> file and recompile the document:</p>

<figure class="picture"><img src="/images/2023/09/bibcop-after.png" style="width:600px;max-width:100%;" alt="picture" /></figure>

<p>This one looks much better to me 
(especially with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_object_identifier">DOI</a>, which 
was not provided by Google Scholar).</p>

<p>By the way, some formatting problems may be auto-fixed by bibcop.
You can use it from the command line, assuming you have your
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.bib</code> file in the current directory:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nv">$ </span>bibcop <span class="nt">--fix</span> <span class="nt">--in-place</span> main.bib
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This command will make as many fixes as possible. 
Then, you can run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bibcop</code> again, from the command line, 
in order to check what style violations are still there:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nv">$ </span>bibcop main.bib
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This will print the same errors as you saw earlier in the LaTeX log.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://ctan.org/pkg/bibcop">In CTAN</a>, you can find full PDF documentation.</p>

<p>You are welcome to suggest additional style checkers, 
via <a href="https://github.com/yegor256/bibcop">GitHub issues</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yegor Bugayenko</name><email>yegor256@gmail.com</email></author><category term="latex" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By the quality of the 'References' section some people may judge the quality of your research paper; bibcop helps you keep everything clean.]]></summary></entry></feed>